<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed</id><updated>2017-07-01 12:38:50</updated><title type="text">Forgotten Roads MX</title><link rel="self" href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog/blog/atom.xml"></link><entry><title>Working with KML and GeoJSON Files</title><updated>2017-07-01 12:38:50</updated><author><name>bobbermac</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2017-07/01-123850/working-with-kml-and-geojson-files.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:Working with KML and GeoJSON Files</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As anyone familiar (not me) with geographic information systems (or "GIS") data can tell you, working with the multitude of data formats, versions of those formats, data entry errors, and inconsistencies, makes GIS data processing a pretty time-consuming task. We've just tried to do very simple things, and it has taken us a few days to get things sorted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Right now at Forgotten Roads, we're evaluating software and data services for use in motorcycle adventure trips. We think we've got a good selection, at least for a first run or two. But before we go into any details on that, we wanted to provide a prelude blog post that can be a head-start for the eager reader and something that we can reference in later posts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Below we'll give a super-quick overview of the main geospatial file formats used by mapping and routes services, and then show you how to work with these files (something that will be very useful when you want to start doing interesting things with your ride routes).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;File Formats&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h4&gt;KML&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Google's ubiquity in so much of the tech world, &lt;code&gt;.kml&lt;/code&gt; files (KML stands for "Keyhole Markup Language") are quite popular. &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keyhole_Markup_Language'&gt;KML&lt;/a&gt; is a type of &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XML'&gt;XML&lt;/a&gt; developed by the company Keyhole, Inc., which specialized in geospatial visualization software. Google bought them in 2004 and turned their product "Earth Viewer" into "Google Earth".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are several versions of this markup language:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Version 2.1 - The last one produced by Google &amp;ndash; this version is still widely used&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Version 2.2 - The first KML version that was submitted to the   &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_Geospatial_Consortium'&gt;Open Geospatial Consortium&lt;/a&gt; (OGC) in 2007&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;2.3 - Published by the OGC in 2015&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most of what we see is still version 2.1.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Really, the thing you need to know about KML is that, among the many, many things that it does, it can specify "traces" or "tracks" (very simple geospatial data, sometimes as little as just latitude and longitude values). The visual routes you see on mapping services like "Google Maps" can be represented in KML files that have this simple data.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;GeoJSON&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the increasing popularity of KML in the mid-2000s, the nearly industry-wide distaste for XML, and rapidly growing adoption of JSON as a preferred human-readable data representation format, a working group for a &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JSON'&gt;JSON&lt;/a&gt;-based geospatial data format was begun in 2007. This gave the world GeoJSON. Then, in 2015, a working group was founded at the &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_Engineering_Task_Force'&gt;IETF&lt;/a&gt; for GeoJSON, which led to an &lt;a href='https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7946'&gt;RFC&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We've been using this format a fair amount, too &amp;ndash; not directly, but because other tools or services we are using work with it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;GPX&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;The last format we'll mention is &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GPS_Exchange_Format'&gt;GPX&lt;/a&gt;. We're not making use of any data in this format, but would remiss if we didn't mention it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Based upon XML, it was created around the same times as KML and stands for "GPS Exchange Format". In continues to enjoy a great deal of popularity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Converting&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Okay, now that we have that boring stuff out of the way, we can talk about MORE BORING STUFF! How do I move from one to the other?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Validating KML&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first thing to keep in mind is that you may download a KML file from a service that has not provided the data fully to spec. Or they may be using an ever older version (and calling it a newer version). This is something that you can check, if you find that services are not letting you upload these KML files.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For instance, if you download a KML file, open it up and check the version number. You should see a line near the top something like the following:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;kml xmlns=&amp;quot;http://earth.google.com/kml/2.1&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;The version number is there at the end. KML is an XML format, and XML file formats are defined with schemas. A quick internet search or two turns up the location for the KML version 2.1 schema here:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://developers.google.com/kml/schema/kml21.xsd'&gt;https://developers.google.com/kml/schema/kml21.xsd&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Here are versions &lt;a href='http://schemas.opengis.net/kml/2.2.0/ogckml22.xsd'&gt;2.2&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href='http://schemas.opengis.net/kml/2.3/ogckml23.xsd'&gt;2.3&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We'll use a command-line tool running in a terminal window for this next bit. The command we'll run is &lt;code&gt;xmllint&lt;/code&gt;. If you have a recent version of Mac OS X with developer tools installed, &lt;code&gt;xmllint&lt;/code&gt; will already be on  your machine. If you are running something like Ubuntu, you may already have &lt;code&gt;libxml2-utils&lt;/code&gt; installed (which includes &lt;code&gt;xmllint&lt;/code&gt;). Here's how you check that the formatting of the KML file is correct:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ xmllint --schema &amp;#126;/Downloads/kml21.xsd &amp;#126;/Downloads/track.kml
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;We downloaded a KML file from &lt;a href='https://spotwalla.com/'&gt;SpotWalla&lt;/a&gt; and found that this command failed on that file. We had to open it up and change a line from this:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;altitudeMode&amp;gt;relative&amp;lt;/altitudeMode&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;to this:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;altitudeMode&amp;gt;relativeToGround&amp;lt;/altitudeMode&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h4&gt;KML -&gt; GeoJSON&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;Probably the easiest way to convert a KML file you have downloaded to GeoJSON is to upload it to the "MyGeodata Converter" service:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://mygeodata.cloud/converter/kml-to-geojson'&gt;https://mygeodata.cloud/converter/kml-to-geojson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Simply browse for your file when you hit the button, then hit "Continue". Once your file uploads, you'll be asked to set any options (the defaults are fine for most cases; we haven't needed to adjust them yet). Then hit the "Convert now!" button, and a &lt;code&gt;.zip&lt;/code&gt; file will download, which you can open up and extract your new &lt;code&gt;.geojson&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The same site offers &lt;a href='https://mygeodata.cloud/converter/geojson-to-gpx'&gt;a GPX converter&lt;/a&gt;, should you need that.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Other Tools&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;We've tried each of the following other tools but they either didn't work for our files or the functionality provided was not quite what we needed. However, they do seem to have a good user following and may be useful for you, so we'll share some links:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://merkaartor.be/'&gt;Merkaartor&lt;/a&gt; - a mapping program that can be used with  &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OpenStreetMap'&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt;; it offers some  import capabilities&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://www.google.com/earth/download/gep/agree.html'&gt;Google Earth Pro&lt;/a&gt; -  Google now provides the "pro" version of their Google Earth software for  free. This is now considered an outdated version; the supported one is the  new Chrome-only Google Earth 9 (released in 2017).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://www.gpsvisualizer.com/map_input?form=googleearth'&gt;GPS Visualizer&lt;/a&gt; -  only used it once, but it seems pretty good.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;KMLCSV - maybe we were doing it wrong, but I wouldn't even bother with this  one ...&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Next Up&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Before too long, you should be seeing another FRMX post about how we use the services that use KML and GeoJSON ... !&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Themes, Categories, and Tags</title><updated>2017-06-28 00:11:03</updated><author><name>bobbermac</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2017-06/28-001103/themes-categories-and-tags.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:Themes, Categories, and Tags</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of things we want to do very well here at Forgotten Roads:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Get out and have some adventures on &lt;strong&gt;America's byways&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Write stories about the &lt;strong&gt;roads, land, and the people&lt;/strong&gt; that we meet and love&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Share our &lt;strong&gt;learning experiences&lt;/strong&gt; so you can have your own adventures sooner, safer, and happier&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get you excited&lt;/strong&gt; about riding and discovery!&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, we wanted to make sure that the articles stayed true to these basic objectives. Just as importantly, we wanted to make sure you knew up front what a post was focused on. That way, if you don't want to read it, you know that right away, and we're not wasting your time. Conversely, if you're interested in a particular topic, it should be easy keep up.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So here's what we've done:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;THEMES&lt;/strong&gt; - There are two "big" types of articles that will get the most emphasis on FRMX.  More than any others, these are the posts that define us and our purpose:&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;"Forgotten Road" posts - these will be articles that cover one road (or route)     that we found special; perfect for a great ride&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;"Excursionist" posts - these will be about interesting people that inspire and     challenge us&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CATEGORIES&lt;/strong&gt; - After the big-ticket items will be more frequent posts  that cover secondary areas of interest, such as events, long trips,  news items, etc.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TAGS&lt;/strong&gt; - While every post will have only one THEME or CATEGORY, each will likely have  several tags. These are simply meant to provide a pointer to the handful of interesting  topics covered in any given post.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;With that, we hope you enjoy what we write for you, and invite you to &lt;a href='/blog/contact.html'&gt;reach out&lt;/a&gt; if you have any ideas or questions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Happy reading! And remember: adventure is out there!&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Update: Lower-48 Challenge</title><updated>2017-06-24 10:55:24</updated><author><name>oubiwann</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2017-06/24-105524/update-lower-48-challenge.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:Update: Lower-48 Challenge</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Wow! &lt;a href='https://www.facebook.com/2ringbike/'&gt;@2ringbike&lt;/a&gt; has made great progress on his &lt;a href='http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog/archives/2017-06/16-170908/the-lower-48-challenge.html'&gt;Lower-48-State Challenge&lt;/a&gt;: last night he was shacked up in Flagstaff, AZ and now he seems to be just minutes from the California border.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He's on day 8 of his 10 day ride &amp;ndash; almost there, 2ringbike! Ride safe!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Update&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;26 June, 2017 0042&lt;/strong&gt;: It looks like, as of about an hour ago, 2ringbike completed his mission! Here's a screenshot of his completed map I just took:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/2ringbike-48-update-2.jpg"&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Congratulations, man!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Get some good sleep and ride home safe :-)&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Dam Ride 2017</title><updated>2017-06-17 21:27:57</updated><author><name>oubiwann</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2017-06/17-212757/dam-ride-2017.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:Dam Ride 2017</id><content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Dam Ride Posts&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='/blog/archives/2017-06/15-223122/dam-ride-2017.html'&gt;Day 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='/blog/archives/2017-06/16-233523/dam-ride-2017.html'&gt;Day 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='/blog/archives/2017-06/17-212757/dam-ride-2017.html'&gt;Day 3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Day 3&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/dam-ride-route-day-3.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This morning we woke to find our bikes had been thoroughly washed by the rain, which was actually quite nice :-) As folks donned their rain gear, there was some discussion about just heading down SD-34 and then straight over to Sioux Falls to avoid the weather. Fortunately, the consensus evolved towards finishing the full ride, and we soon headed out into the cloudy morning, our tanks brimming with petrol.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pierre is a small city, and within moments we were in open land. SD-34 is a nice road, and since it follows the Missouri River for a while, it's got a stretch of great scenery. After it pulls away from the river, it passes through the &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crow_Creek_Indian_Reservation'&gt;Crow Creek Reservation&lt;/a&gt; which offers a beauty of its own:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/dam-ride-crow-creek-reservation.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After hanging a right in Fort Thompson towards the Missouri, we stopped at the &lt;a href='http://www.crowcreekconnections.org/photos.html'&gt;Spirit of the Circle Monument&lt;/a&gt; (dedicated to the loss of Santee Lakota lives in the aftermath of the Dakota War of 1862). This was my second visit to the site; it is a rightfully somber but peaceful place. Then we headed across the river and stopped at the bottom of &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Bend_Dam'&gt;Big Bend Dam&lt;/a&gt;, continuing westward after snapping a picture of the group.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So far, the stretch of road we'd done that morning had been some of the best riding of the whole event: the temperature had dropped quite a bit, making the quite comfortable (I prefer cool rides); no rain yet, even though everyone in the group but me was in rain gear (I was in my leathers; I often don't care if I get wet while riding ... unless I'm camping for the night!). The roads were smooth, there was no traffic, the group seemed in good spirits, and the land engulfing us was beautiful and peaceful.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As nice as that was, it was about to get better :-) On SD-47, especially once we passed under and were south of Interstate 90, and as we got up into the hills in that area. Google Street View can't really capture it, but this &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; give you a sense of it:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/dam-ride-hwy-47-sd.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mark and I had swapped out the sweep position, so I'd been in the back, but as we moved down 47, I kept loosing track of place and time and would often find that I'd eased off the throttle so much that the group was way ahead. It brought a smile to my face a few times when I'd caught up and saw that the &lt;em&gt;whole group&lt;/em&gt; was spread out like that ... as if we were expanding to drink it all in, each person riding in their own private vastness :-)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After that section of the road when we filled up in Gregory, SD several of us expressed the same sentiment: let's go back and ride that again!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You will definitely be seeing a dedicated "Forgotten Road" post from me on SD-47 ... with tons of pictures and notes on things to look for when you are riding through that beautiful, open country.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While we were filling up at the station, we had a nice conversation with a local farmer; we'd told him how amazed we were with the ride, what special country it was, and he beamed with a soft pride. There was a nice bond we formed in loving that land, land that he quite obviously took a special pride and honor in.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a bonus, he shared with us his favourite place to eat down the road in Pickstown. None of us willing to skip lunch like we'd done the day before, we eagerly hopped on our bikes in search Abby's.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/dam-ride-abbys.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yup, that's Abby's. I gotta say, when we passed the steakhouse/burger place with the "Biker's Welcome" sign and instead pulled into a gas station for eats, I had some serious doubts. However, there are a bunch of tables inside and a couple short-order cooks in an ample kitchen. The service was prompt and very friendly. As we waited for our food the place &lt;strong&gt;really&lt;/strong&gt; filled up; by the time we were stuffing our faces with the best lunch of the ride, the joint was packed. We thanked that farmer for the tip, wherever he was then :-)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While in Abby's, the rain had finally caught up to us with some gentle sprinkles sending us off to see the last dam of our ride: &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gavins_Point_Dam'&gt;Gavins Point Dam&lt;/a&gt;. The area around this dam was quite nice &amp;ndash; very family oriented; lots of folks obviously having a wonderful time. The surrounding parkland was open, spacious, inviting, and with lots of it. Seemed like a great place to spend a Sunday afternoon, just hangin' out :-)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With our mission accomplished (visiting all four of the dams on the main route), feeling more rain coming, and ready to be home, we set off. The rain really started coming down as we headed up US-81 &amp;ndash; I was feeling it pretty good, since I'd forgotten to put my keffiyeh back over my lower face after stopping at the dam.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the sky darkened further, and the sky set in for a good pour, we ran into impassable construction and were directed to turn around. This was actually a bonus for me, since I love riding through Viborg and taking smaller country roads home (81's too fast with too much traffic for my taste!)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The rain kept coming down harder and harder, until one point where, just as we came into Sioux Falls, it became a sheer wall of water we were riding through. Seemed like a great way to end a good ride on a hot summer's evening :-) (though I may stand alone with that opinion ... !)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We went our separate ways, changed up, dried off, and then headed over to Lonnie Entenman's (the "L" of "J&amp;L Harley Davidson") secret HD-Cave, chock full of Harley-Davidson memorabilia. I've never seen anything like it ... maybe I can talk him into an interview and a tour with pictures, so I can share it here; it's really something to see.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here's my favourite piece in the place:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/dam-ride-collection.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We all shared our last meal of the event together, told stories, laughed at jokes, and had a really wonderful time together. This was a great event with just the best folks you could want to hang out with, and I'm already looking forward to next year's ride (which may be a trip out to the Black Hills! Hellllo, CAMPING!)&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Dam Ride 2017</title><updated>2017-06-16 23:35:23</updated><author><name>oubiwann</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2017-06/16-233523/dam-ride-2017.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:Dam Ride 2017</id><content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Dam Ride Posts&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='/blog/archives/2017-06/15-223122/dam-ride-2017.html'&gt;Day 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='/blog/archives/2017-06/16-233523/dam-ride-2017.html'&gt;Day 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='/blog/archives/2017-06/17-212757/dam-ride-2017.html'&gt;Day 3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Lindenwood Campground&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sleep was a bit fitful last night for me, as it always is when camping in the open without a tent, especially when it's been a while. The noises of nearby Interstate 94 didn't actually bother me, since I had earplugs with me. At 5am I decided I wasn't going to get back to sleep, so I hopped out of the hammock and did my morning routine &amp;ndash; and boy was I glad I did! This is the sunrise that greeted me when I'd finished up:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/dam-ride-sunrise.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My camping neighbor/fellow rider and I packed up and set off about the same time, but we parted ways on the road as he headed off to begin his Lower 48 States challenge and I rode down to the local Harley-Davidson store to meet up with the others joining the Dam Ride.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Day 2&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/dam-ride-route-day-2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the troops slowly made their way in, coffee and donuts helped wake folks up and riding groups started to take shape. It was a slow, casual start and our group was ready to head out around 930am. Sadly, we had decided to take Interstate 94 west (I'm a byways person myself), but fortunately it was just for a few miles.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Shortly after that, we were heading south on country roads like this:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/dam-ride-hwy-1-nd.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(The pics I'd taken at the campground were the only ones for the rest of the trip, so all the rest will be from Google Street View ...)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We made several quick stops for gas, refreshments, visits to the loo, map checks, etc.  Sadly we never stopped for lunch. We did hit some rain, but it was light an we didn't gear up. It felt really nice :-)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At one point, the guy riding sweep (Mark &amp;ndash; we rode together on Day 1 to Fargo) fell back to the point where I lost sight of him. I stopped and pulled a U-ey on the highway and headed back. Almost immediately I caught sight of him, so turned around again. Pretty far behind now, he and I stopped shortly after that when he pulled up next to me and let me know my hydration pack was open at the top and stuff was peeking out.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Well, it turns out that the reason he had stopped the &lt;em&gt;first&lt;/em&gt; time was because he'd seen something fly out and land on the side of the road &amp;mdash; and, of course, it turned out to  be mine! I still owe him a drink for that ...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The roughest part of the ride for everyone (many jokes were made about it at the tailgate party tonight) was the stretch of road along the Missouri river between the area around Forest City, SD and our first dam &amp;ndash; primarily South Dakota Highway 1804:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/dam-ride-sd-1804.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was warm, the scenery didn't seem to change at all, and everyone's energy felt low.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We were all pretty wiped by the time we got to &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oahe_Dam'&gt;Oahe Dam&lt;/a&gt;, so it was nice to stretch and hang out at the visitor's center for a while. We got a nice impromptu tutorial of some high-water events from one of the women who worked there, and that was pretty interesting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As we were gearing up for the final stretch into Pierre, a woman on a Harley trike and her grandson were pulling into the parking lot, the little boy staring wide-eyed at us. We chatted with her a bit, and then asked her shy rider "Hey buddy, how you likin' the ride?" He threw both arms up into the air and yelled out with glee "Weeee-heee!" This cracked all of us up and we gave him cheers of encouragement :-)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After bidding our new friends a safe ride, we were on our way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ride into Pierre was quick, and we were soon at the &lt;a href='https://goo.gl/ndtQ5D'&gt;Ramkota Hotel&lt;/a&gt;, checked in, bikes parked, some of us in shorts, but all of us hanging out in the parking lot with the Fargo HD truck and trailer enjoying free beers, hard ciders, and pop.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Next, we headed over to &lt;a href='https://goo.gl/3JhXbT'&gt;Guadalajara Mexican Restaurant&lt;/a&gt;. It was pretty good (I have to make allowances at Mexican food joints, since I spent the first eight years of my life eating enchiladas in San Diego county), but since we'd missed lunch, I ate waaay more than I should have. They served Modelo Negra, which was a great and unexpected treat &amp;ndash; it's one of my faviourite Mexican beers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One sad thing that happened as we were coming into Pierre was that a young man had gotten into an accident on a motorcycle. A couple in our group from Parker, SD were with us at this point, one of whom had been an EMT for years (now retired; their bike is decked out in a pretty cool EMT-themed paint job). They quickly ran over to assist and were there before the first responders. Fortunately the young man wasn't seriously injured, though he did seem to have a fractured pelvis. Our EMT buddy latter told us that the accident had occurred when a driver ran a red light and clipped the rider (who was a car salesman; he was only out on the road to evaluate the motorcycle which was being used as a trade-in for a car).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was really fantastic to see members of our group leap into action to help those in need. It's also nice to know you're riding with such good people :-)&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>The Lower-48 Challenge</title><updated>2017-06-16 17:09:08</updated><author><name>oubiwann</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2017-06/16-170908/the-lower-48-challenge.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:The Lower-48 Challenge</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Shortly after I started riding a motorcycle, I heard about the &lt;a href='http://www.hokaheychallenge.com/index.html'&gt;Hoka Hey Challenge&lt;/a&gt; (more on this later!). Researching that &amp;ndash; and endurance riding in general &amp;ndash; led me to the &lt;a href='http://www.ironbutt.com/'&gt;Iron Butt Association&lt;/a&gt; web site and their rides/certifications. So, when I pulled into my campsite last night and found that I was bivouacked next to someone doing the IBA's &lt;a href='http://www.ironbutt.com/themerides/48n10/'&gt;48 States Series&lt;/a&gt;, I was quite chuffed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='https://www.facebook.com/2ringbike/'&gt;@2ringbike&lt;/a&gt; seems a private man (he didn't give his name, and I didn't ask), but he was eager to have a quiet chat with another rider.  He'd just left home in Saskatchewan, Canada yesterday ... and was already sharing his ride status with his kids and wife (via &lt;a href='https://spotwalla.com/index.php'&gt;SpotWalla&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href='http://bubblergps.com/'&gt;Bubbler GPS&lt;/a&gt;).  He's also riding with a GoPro which is configured to take a still shot every few seconds; he plans on compiling these into a video time-lapse of his trip and putting it on YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This morning he starts on his journey of the lower 48 states. He's going to hop across the state border to Minnesota, then come back to North Dakota and head down to South Dakota, then on to Nebraska and points East after that.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was delighted to be there at the start of his journey, and play some small role in his story &amp;ndash; last night we used my phone's Yelp app (so that he didn't have to pay exorbitant international data fees) to find a coffeeshop where he can get his first certification today.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I can't think of a more excellent way to begin a morning ride than with a cappuccino :-)&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Dam Ride 2017</title><updated>2017-06-15 22:31:22</updated><author><name>oubiwann</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2017-06/15-223122/dam-ride-2017.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:Dam Ride 2017</id><content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Dam Ride Posts&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='/blog/archives/2017-06/15-223122/dam-ride-2017.html'&gt;Day 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='/blog/archives/2017-06/16-233523/dam-ride-2017.html'&gt;Day 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='/blog/archives/2017-06/17-212757/dam-ride-2017.html'&gt;Day 3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Three-day HOG-sponsored Ride&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last year the local HOG sponsored a group ride that visited some of the hydro-electric dams in South Dakota, but I wasn't able to go. This year, I took time off from work to make sure I could participate in the three-day ride with three sister HOG chapters. I lucked out, because this year was a full-on event, complete with pin set, tail-gate party, sponsored meals, and support vehicles (which fortunately weren't needed).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;The Route&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since the starting point is in Fargo, ND this year, those of us riding up from Sioux Falls and Glacier Lakes got an early start on our ride. More on that below. The &lt;em&gt;official&lt;/em&gt; ride starts from Fargo, ND with open ended routes across the state to the Missouri and down into South Dakota for a night in Pierre.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The next day is a ride across Native reservations, ranch land, and country roads, the James River valley, Yankton, and up to Sioux Falls.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Preparation&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;On my last multi-day ride (3500+ miles), I was brand-new to distance riding and had quite the adventure with bags and packing &amp;ndash; not only was the trip on short notice, I didn't have any proper bags. All winter I'd been musing about bag arrangement and packing for my cruiser (Softail Slim S). That's a saga that will get a post of its own, but for now I will say that I put a LOT of thinking into the packing and preparation for this smaller ride ... it's going to be the first test of the next iteration of my packing system.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In my eagerness to see if everything fit (it did!), I got it all packed before taking any photos, but at the last minute my wife did remind me to get a shot of the gear that I will be wearing:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/dam-ride-gear-layout.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bright and early, a buddy from the local HOG group and I headed out, everything fully secure and packed tight:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/dam-ride-pre.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Day 1&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/dam-ride-route-day-1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We decided to take a scenic route just across the Minnesota border that would put us into Ortonville in time for lunch. This was my second trip up through this area (the first time was to visit the grave of Medal of Honor war hero &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Woodrow_W._Keeble'&gt;Woodrow Keeble&lt;/a&gt;). Last fall when I stopped in Ortonville they were having their annual corn harvest festival. This time was comparatively sedate, but even more delicious: we had burgers at the excellent &lt;a href='https://goo.gl/pZECGS'&gt;Headwaters Grill &amp; Bar&lt;/a&gt;. Yet another good reason to stop in Ortonville!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The post-lunch ride was really fantastic &amp;ndash; nothing earth-shattering like riding the Rockies or Highway 1 to Big Sur, but just plain fun with beautiful scenery along &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Stone_Lake'&gt;Big Stone Lake&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lake_Traverse'&gt;Lake Traverse&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This last leg of the journey was a bit windy and we sometimes got smacked pretty hard, but the views were so great that the time passed without even feeling it; before we knew it, we were in Fargo. We may actually have been the first riders to arrive:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/dam-ride-fargo.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This gave me enough time to head over to &lt;a href='http://www.fargoparks.com/facilities-recreation/lindenwood-campground.html'&gt;Lindenwood Campground&lt;/a&gt; where they gave me a great site right on the &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Red_River_of_the_North'&gt;Red River&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/dam-ride-red-river.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/dam-ride-camp-site.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Next up was a return to Harley-Davidson of Fargo for the kick-off party+BBQ,  then back to the campsite to set up the hammock, meet &lt;a href='/blog/archives/2017-06/16-170908/the-lower-48-challenge.html'&gt;2ringbike&lt;/a&gt;, and get some shut-eye:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/dam-ride-hammock.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Nation of Patriots 2017</title><updated>2017-06-07 16:59:57</updated><author><name>oubiwann</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2017-06/07-165957/nation-of-patriots-2017.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:Nation of Patriots 2017</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/nat-of-pats-logo-med.jpg" style="float: right;" &gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='/blog/archives/2016-08/25-174345/nation-of-patriots-2016.html'&gt;Last year&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href='http://www.nationofpatriots.com/'&gt;Nation of Patriots&lt;/a&gt; tour came through Sioux Falls, I participated in the mini-parade we took down to the &lt;a href='http://www.siouxfalls.org/veterans-memorial.aspx'&gt;Sioux Falls Veterans' Memorial Park&lt;/a&gt;. We did the same thing this year, but then several of us also rode down to Nebraska for the next passing of the flag ceremony, too.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This year was a bit different &amp;ndash; we were the sixth stop from the start, as opposed to last year where we were the sixth from the last :-) Here's this year's tour path:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/nat-of-pats-2017-path.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As such, the riders came in from Watertown, SD this year instead of Nebraska, to meet us at &lt;a href='http://www.jl-harley.com/'&gt;J&amp;L Harley-Davidson&lt;/a&gt; (not unlike the path taken by &lt;a href='/blog/archives/2017-06/24-105524/update-lower-48-challenge.html'&gt;2ringbike&lt;/a&gt; for his lower-48 IBA challenge ...):&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/nat-of-pats-2017-jlharley.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(photo from the Nation of Patriots Flickr &lt;a href='https://www.flickr.com/photos/149200032@N04/34598215283/in/album-72157682281779824/'&gt;photo stream&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Passing of the Flag in Sioux Falls&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://media.graytvinc.com/images/690*388/patriot+ride.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Photo credit: &lt;a href='http://www.ksfy.com/content/news/Patriot-Ride-stops-in-Sioux-Falls-Tuesday&amp;ndash;426893231.html'&gt;KSFY/ABC Sioux Falls&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I arrived at J &amp; L, I was stunned by how many folks were there, ready to make a parade down to the Veterans' Park! We even had a police escort &amp;ndash; this was a much bigger deal than last year, and it was really nice to see. I think there might have been 20-30 bikes this time (as opposed to the small handful in 2016).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The flag-passing ceremony was nice, recognizing our veterans and give some history/context of the mission of Nation of Patriots. Afterwards,  just like last time, we all signed the book at the park (but no banner was traveling with the flag this year).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;J&amp;L sponsored burgers and dogs for vets up at the "Harley Fort" on 60th, so a bunch of us headed back up after the ceremony. I got to chat with a couple of vets that hadn't been here last year, but had heard of the event this time due to the efforts of the Vietnam/Legacy Vets MC and J &amp; L Harley-Davidson.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;The Ride Down to Norfolk, NE&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The next day I took a day off from work so I could ride with the group down to Norfolk for the next passing of the flag ceremony. This was a great ride, since we didn't take the highway. Lots of great country to ride through, between here and there. Even better, we stopped in Yankton, SD for lunch where &lt;a href='http://jodeans.com/'&gt;JoDean's Steakhouse &amp; Buffet&lt;/a&gt; sponsored lunch for the whole crew! Thanks, JoDean's :-)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I sat with the American Legion commander for Norfolk, NE and he was just the nicest guy I'd hung out with in ages &amp;ndash; if the Norfolk crew is anything like him, they must be a wonderful bunch to work and ride with!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From Yankton we headed down 81 into Nebraska, eventually making our way to the &lt;a href='https://veterans.nebraska.gov/norfolk-veterans-home'&gt;Norfolk Veterans' Home&lt;/a&gt; where they were having a whole-day mini-fair: goats and calves for the kids to pet, balloon sculpture, free lemonade, gunny sack races, big band music, and even a little dancing! There were at least 4 generations represented there; what a wonderful gift to the veterans staying in that home (and it really felt like a &lt;i&gt;home&lt;/i&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After we had a chance to chat, meet some folks, and have some lemonade, we held the ceremony:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/nat-of-pats-2017-1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/nat-of-pats-2017-2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;The Sioux Falls Return Trip&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;After some more mingling and saying goodbye to our new Norfolk friends, we plotted courses back to Sioux Falls. The guys from the MC wanted to zip back up via I-29 (not a fan), so three others of us looked for a scenic route &amp;ndash; which we found!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This was the best riding of the whole two days: all backroads, some time on the &lt;a href='http://nebraskaoutlawtrail.org/'&gt;Outlaw Trail&lt;/a&gt; (a Nebraska Scenic Byway), beautiful hills, some nice curving roads, cute little towns &amp;ndash; in other words, everything you'd want in a ride :-)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Funnily enough, even though we took our sweet time, when we were gassing up in Vermilion, SD we saw the guys from the MC pass by on their way to I-29. We waved, but then continued our ride directly north, taking in the sights and smells, ending our participation this year in the best way: remembering our fellow veterans, freedom of the road, and riding with friends :-)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can find the Nation of Patriots on social media at the following locations:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://twitter.com/NationoPatriots'&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://www.facebook.com/Nation-of-Patriots-193006514043230/'&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://www.flickr.com/photos/149200032@N04/albums'&gt;Flickr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>The Beginning of a New Project</title><updated>2016-09-19 22:13:43</updated><author><name>bobbermac</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2016-09/19-221343/the-beginning-of-a-new-project.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:The Beginning of a New Project</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the things that I enjoy most about riding a motorcycle is the adventure; however, I don't ride a dual-sport bike; I ride a cruiser. I love the old look of the bobber motorcycles, but I like heading off into the unknown on forgotten byways and country roads &amp;ndash; tying a tarp to the bike as lean-to when it's time to rest, and then packing up in the dawn light for another day of sights and smells of the less-traveled lands.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It seems that I'm not alone in this, yet there aren't many places online where one can read stories, take inspiration, or plan for the next such adventure. So, I thought it might be nice to provide one.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Forgotten Roads is for &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; type of rider who's looking for kindred spirits of the tarmac, gravel, and dirt. We're not an MC, but rather an &lt;em&gt;MX&lt;/em&gt;; not a club, but a resource for the &lt;em&gt;motorcycle excursionist&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the coming months (and years!) you can expect posts on this blog that cover everything from personal adventures and stories to group events and rides; from lessons learned and hard-one personal experience to produce reviews. Of particular interest, we will be sharing excellent roads for riding, and how to get to them, as well as friendships and acquaintances we form with random fellow excursionists we meet on these forgotten roads.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Nation of Patriots 2016</title><updated>2016-08-25 17:43:45</updated><author><name>oubiwann</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2016-08/25-174345/nation-of-patriots-2016.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:Nation of Patriots 2016</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Every year in Sioux Falls, &lt;a href='http://www.jl-harley.com/'&gt;J&amp;L Harley-Davidson&lt;/a&gt; takes part in the &lt;a href='http://www.nationofpatriots.com/'&gt;Nation of Patriots&lt;/a&gt; tour through the lower 48 contiguous states of the US. It starts on &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Memorial_Day'&gt;Memorial Day&lt;/a&gt; and takes about 100 days to complete, covering nearly 15,000 miles in the process.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href='http://www.nationofpatriots.com/tour'&gt;their site&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt; Every year Nation of Patriots&amp;trade; organizes a national effort that pays tribute to, and honors, all of America's Armed Forces - Past, Present, and Fallen. This united effort is known as the Patriot Tour&amp;trade;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Patriot Tour&amp;trade; traditionally begins during Memorial Day weekend. A massive group of riders escorts one American Flag on the back of a motorcycle to the first of many destinations. Upon arrival, the flag is transferred to the new escort. The next day the Flag is escorted to another designated location...and on and on for over 100 days, through all 48 continental states. The Flag finally makes it full circle and lands right back in WI where several thousand Americans gather to honor America's Military members and raise support for those wounded in their service. This is the Patriot Tour&amp;trade;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's the very foundation of the American Flag and all it represents that our brave men and women in the military have stood and died defending, continue to stand and protect, and will forever fight for. &lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The flag arrived today from Nebraska and we had a small group gathered at the &lt;a href='http://www.siouxfalls.org/veterans-memorial.aspx'&gt;Sioux Falls Veterans' Memorial Park&lt;/a&gt;. The group consisted of members from the Vietnam/Legacy Vets MC, H.O.G. Chapter members, employees from J&amp;L, and local veterans. The crew from the MC lead the ride from J&amp;L to the memorial park where we held the passing of the flag ceremony:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/nat-of-pats-2016-1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/nat-of-pats-2016-2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/nat-of-pats-2016-3.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Afterwards, we rode back up to J&amp;L where we signed the banner that was getting passed this year with the flag, talked about the ride up to Watertown tomorrow (where the next flag-passing will occur), and hung out.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The guys from the MC were great, and I got a bunch of their cards. I hope to ride with them again sometime.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Looking forward to participating in the Nation of Patriots next year, too!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can find the Nation of Patriots on social media at the following locations:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://twitter.com/NationoPatriots'&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://www.facebook.com/Nation-of-Patriots-193006514043230/'&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Knucklehead at Sturgis</title><updated>2016-07-31 11:49:41</updated><author><name>oubiwann</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2016-07/31-114941/knucklehead-at-sturgis.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:Knucklehead at Sturgis</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My wife and I were camping in the Black Hills this weekend, just as Sturgis is kicking into gear, and there are some amazing bikes on the road &amp;ndash; tons of group rides going on. The best sight of the day, though, has been the group of vintage Harleys and Indians we saw stopped at a burger joint on the side of the road. I pulled over real quick to snap some photos ...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/arctic-knucklehead-front.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The owner was chatting with another fellow, so I didn't get a chance to say much more than how much I liked is ride, but I did overhear that he had taken two trips to the Arctic Circle with his Knucklehead, and had put something far over 100,000 miles on it, with 2,600 miles of that being gravel roads. The second trip to the Arctic he had done for a buddy who wanted to make the trip with him.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/arctic-knucklehead-side.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He loves adventure riding with the Knucklehead because it's so easy to fix: every time he's had a breakdown, he's been able to get it up and running with the tools he carried on him, even if just to limp along to the nearest garage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm kind of bummed that I only got the boots of the one guy - he was riding an Indian with a group of others, all of them dressed up in period racing gear. What a site! I guess I'll have to go back next year and get more photos :-)&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>