<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed</id><updated>2017-08-13 19:36:59</updated><title type="text">Forgotten Roads MX</title><link rel="self" href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog/blog/atom.xml"></link><entry><title>It's a Saddle, Not a Couch</title><updated>2017-08-13 19:36:59</updated><author><name>oubiwann</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2017-08/13-193659/it-s-a-saddle-not-a-couch.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:It's a Saddle, Not a Couch</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The question I get asked more than any other about my bike doesn't have to do with the paint job, the 110 cu (1800+ cc) motor, or the Firestone clone tyres (Avon's). Instead, the most common point of interest relates to the seat in some way, anything from "is that comfortable?" or "how do you do that?" to "fuuuuuck, no ..."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;The Ride&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite what one might imagine simply by looking at it, it's very comfortable: I ride with it regularly on bad roads, over potholes, gravel washboards, and dirt. I sometimes catch air (usually one wheel at a time &amp;ndash; once I got both &amp;ndash; and this invariably leads my butt leaving the seat by a few inches). In all cases, the cushion provided by the springs has made for a soft landing and a generally good riding experience.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now, without question, after riding a couple hundred miles, my butt and thighs really need a break. I'll take 20-30 minutes when I gas up to stretch out. Sometimes, on a bad ride (no scenery change, drowsiness, general low-energy) it takes me a few moments to throw a leg over and get out of the saddle.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;The Saddle&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here's the thing, though &amp;ndash; as the title of this post says: this is not actually a "seat" in the standard, stock Harley-Davidson sense of the word (certainly not from the perspective of touring riders). This is a saddle in the full-on cowboy, rough-rider sense of the word. In fact, &lt;a href='https://www.harley-davidson.com/store/bobber-solo-saddle'&gt;the product page&lt;/a&gt; uses that word explicitly. I've you've ever ridden a horse all day, you'll know exactly what I'm talking about. If you loved that, you'll love this seat ... even when it hurts :-)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;More thoughts below, but here are more pics:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/34916417473/in/datetaken/" title="2017-06-27 19.08.00"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4215/34916417473_0be96d8682_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1536" alt="2017-06-27 19.08.00"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/35338978380/in/datetaken/" title="2017-06-27 19.08.20"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4053/35338978380_323fc80d9f_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1536" alt="2017-06-27 19.08.20"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/35686161756/in/datetaken/" title="2017-06-27 19.08.48"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4008/35686161756_760f5ef822_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1536" alt="2017-06-27 19.08.48"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;A Philosophy of Experience&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Admittedly, I do have a slightly non-standard riding aesthetic: I like it gritty and real. I want to feel the roads, with all their imperfections. I want to smell not only the ponderosa pines and open prairie in bloom, but also the horse and cow manure of passing farms. One isn't good, nor is the other bad &amp;ndash; they're just all part of the ride, part of the experience. I'm riding because I love it, because in the modern world it's tough to find authentic, unfiltered, untamed experiences. The bobber saddle definitely provides an untamed, unfiltered experience of the road, in all its glory and imperfections.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This approach has born up well in the last 15,000 miles or so &amp;ndash; across all types of land and in all sorts of weather (including light snowfall). The worst dirt roads I've ridden in any vehicle, I've tackled on the bobber seat, not only with no regrets, but with lots of good times and a few good stories :-)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Customizing the Seat&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Well, there's not much more to it than leather, steel, and springs. Which means we can tweak two out of three. Meatloaf always said that wasn't bad.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you're familiar with the H-D saddle, you'll remember it's black ... and the one pictured above looks a little different. I've applied countless layers of two different kinds of leather conditioner and brown heavy-duty dye. I've used brown leather on the rest of the bike and have dyed my chaps and jacket to match those, so it was a natural next step for the seat. I've known guys who chose to reupholster their saddles to get the color of brown they wanted, but the dying route has given me just what I was looking for and at a fraction of the cost (although there was increased initial maintenance and care required).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, I never had any dye come off on my pants, even in extreme weather conditions. I think this is largely due to the quality of the dye and leather protection, but also to the manner of application:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Before dying sessions, I would thoroughly clean the seat.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Let the dye completely dry for several hours in a 90+F garage,&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Do several rounds of leather protection:&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Bickmore conditioner first (it's much wetter)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Let it soak in&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Give it a good rub&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Let it dry a bit&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Apply a generous amount of the Red Wing conditioner (thick layer coating     the entire surface)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Let the leather absorb it&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Rub it in for 10 to 15 minutes with an old rag).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;After a long ride, I'll use some saddle soap to clean it up a bit. It hasn't needed any more dye this year, and I've only conditioned it once (right before the riding season started). I have had to re-dye my chaps and jacket, though that's expected, since they bear the brunt of the action (no windshield).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The other thing I did to customise the saddle was simply give the springs a coat metallic aged bronze spray paint: can't get more budget than that. Surprisingly, after 4000 miles of riding with that coat, there's only a few dings in the paint, and I only noticed that this week after doing a very close inspection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Preferred Leather Products&lt;/h2&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Online Mapping Tools for Your Ride</title><updated>2017-07-29 12:59:10</updated><author><name>bobbermac</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2017-07/29-125910/online-mapping-tools-for-your-ride.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:Online Mapping Tools for Your Ride</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Previous posts have touched on some of the map- and route-related tooling and services available for free online, that can help map out your ride. We'll mention them again here, but also &amp;ndash; and more importantly &amp;ndash; introduce you to to a free service we haven't covered yet, one that we now depend upon heavily for recording our tracks across the country.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;From the site's &lt;a href='https://www.openstreetmap.org/about'&gt;About&lt;/a&gt; page:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;   OpenStreetMap is built by a community of mappers that contribute and   maintain data about roads, trails, cafes, railway stations, and much more,   all over the world. &lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;OpenStreetMap allows you to upload limited forms of &lt;code&gt;.kml&lt;/code&gt; files; depending upon your needs, it could be all you're looking for.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;OpenSourceService&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='https://www.openrouteservice.org'&gt;OpenRouteService&lt;/a&gt; utilizes the data from OpenStreetMap to help users define and generate multi-destination map routes taking into consideration numerous modes of transportation. It also provides for a greater number of road types your route should ignore (e.g., unpaved, fords, tracks).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Like OpenStreetMap, OpenRouteService lets you upload files. It is not as strict in how it parses &lt;code&gt;.kml&lt;/code&gt; as OpenStreetMap but we have found issues (bugs) in rendering routes that cause a displayed map to not always match the exact data in the uploaded file. This was a show-stopper for us, but maybe not for others.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Depending upon what you wish to accomplish, you also may need to convert your track or trip files from one format to another. We've run into a few minor rough edges there, but serious.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;SpotWalla&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spotwalla is our golden child at FRMX: we use an iOS app called &lt;a href='http://rvtechtools.com/swconnect.html'&gt;SWConnect&lt;/a&gt; that was originally designed for use with RVs. The Android app for SpotWalla is called &lt;a href='http://bubblergps.com/'&gt;Bubbler GPS&lt;/a&gt; and seems quite nice (putting the iOS app to shame, some say). We first found out about SpotWalla when oubiwann met 2ringbike in a Fargo campground as 2ringbike was preparing to set out on his lower-48 ride.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While the SpotWalla service was nice and usable, we almost gave up when we couldn't get SWConnect to make any more frequent updates than every 5 minutes. However, after some digging online we found instructions from the author of SWConnect. His recommendation was to use overlays.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To do this, you set up a trip as usual on the SpotWalla site (for a certain day or range of days). These will be the updates that are, by default, will be sent every 5 minutes. Then, when you're ready to start your trip, open up SWConnect on the iPhone:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Touch "Application Setup"&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Log in to SpotWalla&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Select the device&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enable track overlay&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Optionally, enable auto track mode&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Touch "Return to Main Screen"&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Touch "Enable Tracking"&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;That should do it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What this does is:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Start sending the large "spot" messages to SpotWalls, every 5 minutesassociated with whatever &lt;strong&gt;trip&lt;/strong&gt; you created for the current date and time(range),&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Creates a new &lt;strong&gt;track&lt;/strong&gt; for the current date/time&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Batches GPS lat/long data in small messages to SpotWalla&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both can later be downloaded as &lt;code&gt;.kml&lt;/code&gt; files and viewed together in as two layers in a single map for any mapping software or service that supports this (many do).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Google "My Maps"&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Google "My Maps" &lt;a href='https://www.google.com/maps/about/mymaps/'&gt;about page&lt;/a&gt; doesn't really say much about the product, but basically it allows you to create and share customized maps. Really, the only driver for Forgotten Roads was "can we completely stylize these maps?". The answer was "yes", so we used it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The additional benefits really make our lives easy, though:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Quickly upload SpotWalla &lt;code&gt;.kml&lt;/code&gt; files, and thus&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Assemble multiple trips and tracks into a single map&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Easily customize the colors of tracks&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We've got a whole slew of blog posts in the pipeline that make extensive use of SpotWalla data and "My Maps" to provide trip maps detailing our routes. We couldn't be writing about what we do and how we do it as effectively without these two tools.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Online Topographic Maps&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some of us at FRMX are land-nav nuts, and there's no substitute for a good topo map. In 2009 USGS started a new project to generate topographical maps from 100% digital sources. In all honesty, these don't even compare to the originals (well, the ones published by USGS from 1947 through 1992).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After downloading a whole slew of the new ones in &lt;code&gt;.pdf&lt;/code&gt; format and experiencing acute disappointment, we were on the hunt for good online topo maps. The search didn't take long, though: we quickly found (and then even more quickly fell in love with) &lt;a href='https://mappingsupport.com/p/gmap4-free-online-topo-maps.html'&gt;gmap4&lt;/a&gt; (see the &lt;a href='https://mappingsupport.com/p/gmap4.php'&gt;fullscreen version&lt;/a&gt;). There's so much to say about this tool, and too little room (this post is already getting a bit long). This is a &lt;strong&gt;phenomenal&lt;/strong&gt; project, and we all hope people continue to donate to it, so that it can continue to survive.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here's a screenshot of gmap4 that captures the highest peak in the Black Hills as well as some of the best riding in the region:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/36237577866/in/datetaken/" title="FireShot Capture 009 - Map produced by Gmap4 from mappings_ - https___mappingsupport.com_p_gmap4.php"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4310/36237577866_3563dcbc3b_o.jpg" width="2556" height="1320" alt="FireShot Capture 009 - Map produced by Gmap4 from mappings_ - https___mappingsupport.com_p_gmap4.php"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;This should give you everything you need to get started creating your own ride maps, complete with the GPS info that your device is recording along the way. If we could only pick one, though, it'd have to be SpotWalla.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have a great adventure!&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Styling Your Own Google Map</title><updated>2017-07-28 13:12:26</updated><author><name>bobbermac</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2017-07/28-131226/styling-your-own-google-map.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:Styling Your Own Google Map</id><content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Map Themes&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href='blog/authors/#oubiwann'&gt;oubiwann&lt;/a&gt; has &lt;a href='/blog/archives/2017-07/21-193252/frmx-google-maps-custom-theme.html'&gt;recently posted&lt;/a&gt;, Forgotten Roads has a new Google Maps theme. But why would we do something like that? Well, it's not unlike the need to create a website with a unique look that distinguishes you from everyone else. For most people, this won't be necessary (or even of interest!), but for those who create unique content that revolves around map data, specific locations, or routes between points on a map, having a way to display this that is uniquely "you" is a great way to present a unified experience of your data.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Google Maps Defaults&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;Okay, but doesn't Google have defaults that are good enough? Sure, Google Maps provides several map views:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Street Map view (this is what most of us probably use)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Satellite view (really nice for sanity checks on locations, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Terrain view (shaded views of land features, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;While each of those is very useful in different ways, they don't really let us look at map data differently than what Google has decided for us. But hey, it's probably meets the needs of the vast majority.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Google "My Maps"&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;For those that aren't satisfied with these, you can actually do something more while still using Google's suite of tools. To see an example of this, do the following:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Go to &lt;a href='http://maps.google.com'&gt;http://maps.google.com/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Log in with Google credentials (upper right).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Then click the "hamburger" menu in the upper left (the icon of three horizontal lines).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;In the menu that appears, click "Your Places" then "Maps" &amp;ndash; if you'vecreated any maps, they'll be here: go ahead and click on one. If you don't have any, you can click "Create Map" at the bottom.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;In the new window / tab that opens up, you'll see "layers" section to theright &amp;ndash; click the arrow next to "Base map".&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;At that point, you'll see the following:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/google-base-map-popup.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And these, dear rider, are the map themes that Google has provided to its "My Maps" users. The first three are the ones we're familiar with, listed above. The remaining six, however, may be quite new to you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the small percentage of the Google Maps using population who aren't satisfied with the defaults, this will likely satisfy. But then there's the tiny remainder like us that, well, need something more. Or less, as the case may be.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;OpenRouteService&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;Before exploring our final solution, it's worth mentioning one of the earliest alternative we explored &amp;ndash; not Google at all. We've used &lt;a href='https://www.openstreetmap.org'&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt; before, and unlike Google Maps, it's run by a volunteer effort and has a permissive open license (something that a lot of people care about). They've got a really nice theme that's easy on the eyes:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/36104290042/in/datetaken/" title="Screen Shot 2017-07-30 at 3.06.49pm"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4311/36104290042_dfeecf8de5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="636" alt="Screen Shot 2017-07-30 at 3.06.49pm"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What we &lt;em&gt;didn't&lt;/em&gt; know about, however, was &lt;a href='https://www.openrouteservice.org/'&gt;OpenRouteService&lt;/a&gt; which makes use of OpenStreetMap but offers a new set of themes to choose from when creating a new route.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We had originally settled on this approach instead of putting time into styling our own maps, but sadly, we found a bug in its routing algorithm when we uploaded our own &lt;code&gt;.kml&lt;/code&gt; files. Given that our riding routes are the core of this whole effort, we had to bail.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For those who don't need perfect duplication of routes from &lt;code&gt;.kml&lt;/code&gt; files, we highly recommend this service. It's not as fast as Google, but you are offered the ability to create a greater number of way points than with Google Maps (something which has bothered us in Google Maps for a long time). Furthermore, their map themes are beautiful. Here's four of them looking at the Rapid City metro area:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/35438453884/in/datetaken/" title="montage-openmapservice"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4314/35438453884_3d4df49e51_b.jpg" width="1024" height="633" alt="montage-openmapservice"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That hardly does them justice, though &amp;ndash; you should visit their site.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here are the two we like best for looking at streets:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/35438451804/in/datetaken/" title="Screen Shot 2017-07-30 at 3.13.17pm"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4302/35438451804_9c485a927c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="634" alt="Screen Shot 2017-07-30 at 3.13.17pm"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/36229769776/in/datetaken/" title="Screen Shot 2017-07-30 at 3.13.31pm"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4312/36229769776_10e7011092_b.jpg" width="1024" height="633" alt="Screen Shot 2017-07-30 at 3.13.31pm"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Styling Tools for Google Maps&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, given that all of our attempts to &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; do this ourselves failed, we fell back on a path of more work and greater time investment: creating a custom style for Google Maps. This required the following:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Creating the style and saving the style JSON data&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Uploading the JSON data to a data repository&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Integrating the style with plain Google Maps (&lt;a href='https://developers.google.com/maps/documentation/javascript/tutorial'&gt;getting started&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Integrating the style with track/trip data in Google Maps (&lt;a href='https://developers.google.com/maps/documentation/javascript/kml'&gt;tutorial&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href='https://developers.google.com/maps/documentation/javascript/kmllayer'&gt;guide&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Uploading track/trip data to a data repository&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Creating new pages that reference that data and pull in the Google Maps JavaScript APIs&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;But! We're not going to cover all that here &amp;ndash; other places do that quite well. I just want to mention the tools for creating your own styles. &lt;a href='/blog/authors/#oubiwann'&gt;oubiwann&lt;/a&gt; mentioned them in his recent post about the FRMX styles:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://snazzymaps.com/'&gt;SnazzyMaps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://www.mapstylr.com/'&gt;MapStylr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both of these sites let you create either new styles from scratch or a style based on another one in their archives. We found a style we really liked &lt;a href='https://snazzymaps.com/style/79825/retro-eco'&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and then began modifying it. We used both SnazzyMaps and MapStylr &amp;ndash; their user interface tools a quite good for this, but couldn't find ways in which one definitely our-performed the other ... so we'll likely continue to use them both.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One thing to keep in mind as you play with both style editors: it's going to be very confusing at first, and you'll find yourself editing different parts of the highly nested data wondering what really controls what. It's not you. The data is complex and anti-intuitive. Just keep plugging away at it.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>FRMX Google Maps Custom Theme</title><updated>2017-07-21 19:32:52</updated><author><name>oubiwann</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2017-07/21-193252/frmx-google-maps-custom-theme.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:FRMX Google Maps Custom Theme</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a quick blog post to share two new Google Maps themes we produced here at Forgotten Roads, in the event that our readers might want to use these as well. They've got a "retro" feel to them, designed to be extremely simple (for easy viewing in blog posts) and pleasing to the eye. These two map styles have been published in two locations (on the &lt;a href='https://snazzymaps.com/explore?text=oubiwann&amp;sort=&amp;tag=&amp;color='&gt;Snazzy Maps&lt;/a&gt; &amp; &lt;a href='http://www.mapstylr.com/author/oubiwann/'&gt;MapStylr&lt;/a&gt; sites), and are of two types:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Retro Muted (&lt;a href='https://snazzymaps.com/style/110996/retro-muted'&gt;Snazzy Maps&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href='http://www.mapstylr.com/style/retro-muted/'&gt;MapStylr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Simple Retro Muted with Terrain (&lt;a href='https://snazzymaps.com/style/111010/simple-retro-muted-with-terrain'&gt;Snazzy Maps&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href='http://www.mapstylr.com/style/simple-retro-muted-with-terrain/'&gt;MapStylr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The second one is even more pared down than the first and is what we've settled on for displaying ride data in our blog posts. Below I've included some example views of the style at different zoom levels.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;State Level Zoom&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here's a view of the lower half of South Dakota:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/35436334184/in/datetaken/" title="Screen Shot 2017-07-30 at 1.24.54pm"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4294/35436334184_a5f000756c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="528" alt="Screen Shot 2017-07-30 at 1.24.54pm"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In both this view and the next you can see how we've diminished the visibility of US interstates to a mere hint, really focusing instead on the state routes &amp;ndash; one of the most important sources of good riding!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Metro Area Level Zoom&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;This shows the Rapid City metro area, outlying ranch land, and some of the Black Hills:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/36135619041/in/datetaken/" title="Screen Shot 2017-07-30 at 1.38.45pm"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4299/36135619041_5a2de443dc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="527" alt="Screen Shot 2017-07-30 at 1.38.45pm"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;City Level Zoom&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The next two show city views and two different zoom levels, emphasizing the labeling simplicity:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/36102331332/in/datetaken/" title="Screen Shot 2017-07-30 at 1.39.27pm"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4330/36102331332_d388af0e8f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="523" alt="Screen Shot 2017-07-30 at 1.39.27pm"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/36268951045/in/datetaken/" title="Screen Shot 2017-07-30 at 1.39.52pm"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4306/36268951045_cb15081896_b.jpg" width="1024" height="527" alt="Screen Shot 2017-07-30 at 1.39.52pm"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Beartooth Run, 2017</title><updated>2017-07-07 21:25:40</updated><author><name>oubiwann</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2017-07/07-212540/beartooth-run-2017.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:Beartooth Run, 2017</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today we were up around 4 am, took our time breakfasting, having tea and campsite espresso, performing the morning rituals, and packing. Not too long after 6 am we were on our way, just beating the sun, getting a view of that orangey-pink morning beauty as we were getting back onto US-212:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/35863074105/in/album-72157683434776573/" title="G0012997"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4213/35863074105_bbb6c4631b.jpg" width="320" height="240" alt="G0012997"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class="panel panel-default route-summary"&gt;   &lt;div class="panel-heading"&gt;&lt;h3 class="panel-title"&gt;Day Summary&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/div&gt;   &lt;div class="panel-body"&gt;     &lt;form class="form-horizontal"&gt;       &lt;div class="form-group"&gt;         &lt;label for="summary-start" class="col-sm-3 control-label"&gt;Start:&lt;/label&gt;         &lt;div id="summary-start" class="col-sm-9"&gt; &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Belle_Fourche,_South_Dakota'&gt;Belle Fourche, SD&lt;/a&gt;  6:19 am CDT&lt;/div&gt;       &lt;/div&gt;       &lt;div class="form-group"&gt;         &lt;label for="summary-end" class="col-sm-3 control-label"&gt;End:&lt;/label&gt;         &lt;div id="summary-end" class="col-sm-9"&gt; &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Red_Lodge,_Montana'&gt;Red Lodge, MT&lt;/a&gt;  4:39 pm CDT&lt;/div&gt;       &lt;/div&gt;       &lt;div class="form-group"&gt;         &lt;label for="summary-miles" class="col-sm-3 control-label"&gt;Distance:&lt;/label&gt;         &lt;div id="summary-miles" class="col-sm-9"&gt;374 mi (602 km)&lt;/div&gt;       &lt;/div&gt;       &lt;div class="form-group"&gt;         &lt;label for="summary-food" class="col-sm-3 control-label"&gt;Food:&lt;/label&gt;         &lt;div id="summary-food" class="col-sm-9"&gt; Breakfast @ Riverside Campground in Belle Fourche, SD&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Second Breakfast @ &lt;a href='https://www.tripadvisor.com/Restaurant_Review-g45098-d4914167-Reviews-Cashway_Cafe-Broadus_Montana.html'&gt;Cashway Cafe&lt;/a&gt; in Broadus, MT&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lunch @ &lt;a href='https://www.tripadvisor.com/Restaurant_Review-g45086-d3266456-Reviews-Cham_Thai_Cuisine-Billings_Montana.html'&gt;Thai Cuisine&lt;/a&gt; in Billings, MT&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dinner @ &lt;a href='http://www.redlodgerestaurants.com/red-lodge-pizza-co/'&gt;Red Lodge Pizza Co.&lt;/a&gt; in Red Lodge, MT        &lt;/div&gt;       &lt;/div&gt;       &lt;div class="form-group"&gt;       &lt;label for="summary-photos" class="col-sm-3 control-label"&gt;Photo Album:&lt;/label&gt;         &lt;div id="summary-photos" class="col-sm-9"&gt; &lt;a href='https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/albums/72157683434776573'&gt;Beartooth Run 2017 - Day 2&lt;/a&gt; (Flickr)         &lt;/div&gt;       &lt;/div&gt;     &lt;/form&gt;   &lt;/div&gt;   &lt;div class="panel-heading"&gt;&lt;h3 class="panel-title"&gt;Route Map&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/div&gt;   &lt;div class="panel-body" style="padding:0; margin: 0"&gt;     &lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4436/36256381541_2b06e22b88_k_d.jpg"&gt;   &lt;/div&gt;   &lt;div class="panel-heading"&gt;&lt;h3 class="panel-title"&gt;Beartooth Run, 2017 Series Links&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/div&gt;   &lt;div class="panel-body" style="padding:0; margin: 0"&gt;     &lt;ul&gt;       &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/blog/archives/2017-06/29-115623/beartooth-run-fargo-h-o-g-.html"&gt;Prologue&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;       &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/blog/archives/2017-07/06-193659/beartooth-run-2017.html"&gt;Day 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;       &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/blog/archives/2017-07/07-212540/beartooth-run-2017.html"&gt;Day 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;       &lt;li&gt;Day 3&lt;/li&gt;       &lt;li&gt;Day 4&lt;/li&gt;       &lt;li&gt;Day 5&lt;/li&gt;       &lt;li&gt;Day 6&lt;/li&gt;     &lt;/ul&gt;   &lt;/div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;South Dakota &amp; Wyoming&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the day 2 album on Flickr, there's a picture the GoPro captured of me pointing at a sign:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/35731320501/in/album-72157683434776573/" title="G0012999"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4277/35731320501_a42679e036.jpg" width="500" height="375" alt="G0012999"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was delighted to see that this segment of 212 was called the "Warrior Trail" (even  though I was in the 101st during Desert Storm, one granddad in WWI, and the other in WWII, Korean, and Vietnam wars, my appreciation for the "warrior's way" is actually &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bushido'&gt;philosophical&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kung&lt;i&gt;fu&lt;/i&gt;(term)#Etymology"&gt;nature&lt;/a&gt;, as opposed to martial).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It turns out the naming of U.S. Route 212 &amp;ndash; from Belle Fourche to the Wyoming border &amp;ndash; is a relatively recent change. It was made by the South Dakota Transportation Commission unanimously in 2009, &lt;a href='http://www.capjournal.com/news/dot-designates-highway-as-the-warrior-trail/article_75412450-6f98-5d25-9d99-94e89b1a1344.html'&gt;honoring the Lakota and Northern Cheyenne&lt;/a&gt; who resisted the U.S. policy of forced reservation life, wiping out Custer and decimating his unit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/36220813982/in/album-72157683434776573/" title="G0013032"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4331/36220813982_5440f2da8b_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1536" alt="G0013032"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the sun continued to rise, its rays warmed the sage and the smell across the road was just amazing. One of the great pleasures of riding is smelling the countryside, and one of the best smells of any land, in my opinion, is that of sage in its natural environment. So much more, to have it gently baked like this in the sun ... what an incredible morning!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An hour or so later, the land started to change with less of the prairie and more hills and trees:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/36344133976/in/album-72157683434776573/" title="G0013123"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4433/36344133976_12a797083d_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1536" alt="G0013123"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Montana&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;After another hour of riding, I was ready for some more food &amp;ndash; so in true Hobbit style we stopped for a second breakfast on the far side of Broadus, MT. With more food and coffee, it was time to see more of Montana from the saddle of this iron horse ...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In what felt like no time at all we started getting more altitude:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/36344129866/in/album-72157683434776573/" title="G0023220"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4364/36344129866_c2f14aba2c_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1536" alt="G0023220"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Soon after, though, things slowed to a crawl as I rode through gravel, sand, mud, and partly chewed up asphalt in a line behind others trying to make their way through this road construction. I'd seen a sign warning motorcyclists to find another route ... they didn't mean me, did they? :-)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/36220806662/in/album-72157683434776573/" title="G0023245"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4430/36220806662_6a76fca1a0_q.jpg" width="150" height="150" alt="G0023245"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/36344127846/in/album-72157683434776573/" title="G0023251"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4347/36344127846_3e8d151378_q.jpg" width="150" height="150" alt="G0023251"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/36344123656/in/album-72157683434776573/" title="G0023257"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4352/36344123656_0f3343fdb3_q.jpg" width="150" height="150" alt="G0023257"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/36344122326/in/album-72157683434776573/" title="G0023258"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4403/36344122326_8b71b25a2d_q.jpg" width="150" height="150" alt="G0023258"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To be honest, I really enjoyed this. I'm constantly finding myself on unpaved, "exciting" roads with the Harley. In this particular case, I was met with a very pleasant surprise: the large truck driving immediately in front of me was continually making adjustments of minor potholes, slowing down before bumps that were nothing for a big rig, but which were a big deal for a motorcycle. I felt that he himself was a rider and was acting as a road captain, letting me know what was coming. He really saved my bacon on more than one occasion, too!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I eventually passed him and the truck he was riding with (long after the construction zone), and give them both a big, heart-felt wave. I wish I could buy you two some beers tonight &amp;ndash; thanks for all the help!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;More overpasses, a little more construction, and before too long it was time to get gas again &amp;ndash; this time near the Little Bighorn Battlefield National Monument. We didn't visit, but we did have a great conversation at the gas station with a fellow rider and Native rancher, swapping stories of the road. This has been the best conversation of the ride so far; we probably talked for about 30 or 40 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since this is where US-212 joins with the highway, once we were on the road again, we opted to get off at &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crow_Agency,_Montana'&gt;Crow Agency, MT&lt;/a&gt; and take some more country roads. We rode Crow-St. Xavier Cutoff to 313 and then Old U.S. 87 &amp;ndash; wow! What a road this was. At some point, it's getting a blog post all its own. Definitely the best riding so far.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Billings, MT was an adventure all its own: finding food, getting across town without going on the highway, avoiding construction, etc. We eventually made it through, though, and headed south on 212 toward Red Lodge. The traffic here was unexpectedly slow and dense &amp;ndash; not a good riding experience. Just had to be patient and settle into a fairly low speed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Red Lodge &amp; Campground&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;At long last, though, we rolled into Red Lodge &amp;ndash; and it was well worth the wait. It's a great little town that feels like some of the smaller gems of the Rocky Mountains in Colorado. In fact, Rory said it reminder here of Boulder, CO in the 70s ...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/36220786442/in/album-72157683434776573/" title="G0053643"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4415/36220786442_ec54a0b79c_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1536" alt="G0053643"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then we had to find our campsite ...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/35992185180/in/album-72157683434776573/" title="G0053664"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4402/35992185180_1c68d0e927_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1536" alt="G0053664"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;which took us longer than I care to admit:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/36220781752/in/album-72157683434776573/" title="G0053679"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4406/36220781752_6e43731c56_q.jpg" width="150" height="150" alt="G0053679"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/35992183380/in/album-72157683434776573/" title="G0053683"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4434/35992183380_6fdc20e9ab_q.jpg" width="150" height="150" alt="G0053683"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/36220779282/in/album-72157683434776573/" title="G0053687"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4391/36220779282_395c5d9fc5_q.jpg" width="150" height="150" alt="G0053687"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/36220778242/in/album-72157683434776573/" title="G0053693"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4388/36220778242_bd2792a94e_q.jpg" width="150" height="150" alt="G0053693"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, I had great fun bouncing around on the dirt roads &amp;ndash; something I got to do a bunch today, given that I made so many trips into town and back!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first ride back was to get a chapter picture taken with my bike. Got lots of comments on the bobber seat (as often happens), but with some folks assuming I'd ridden it out to Red Lodge on a different seat, and then swapped it out for the ride up the pass. (Do people do that?) We had some good laughs, then I browsed around town and took some supplies (and a gift!) back to Rory who was chillin' at the campsite.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Beartooth Run Group Dinner&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I returned to town for the first official event of the ride: to meet with the rest of the Fargo H.O.G. chapter for a pizza dinner (sponsored by &lt;a href='http://www.hdfargo.com/'&gt;Harley-Davidson of Fargo&lt;/a&gt;!), lots of great conversation, more than a few jokes, and some presentations (including a returning local guest speaker who was a favourite from a few years prior). One presentation covered the back-story of the Beartooth Ride, even before the 1st annual ride, 24 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Long that, two of the Fargo chapter members had made the trip in 1967 &amp;ndash; more great stories of this particular event were shared, causing much laughter around the room. I managed to snap a couple of pics of the photos that were passed around:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/36021577290/in/album-72157683434776573/" title="iPhone Pics from Beartooth Run 2017"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4424/36021577290_5947849cdb_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1389" alt="iPhone Pics from Beartooth Run 2017"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/35490469260/in/album-72157683434776573/" title="iPhone Pics from Beartooth Run 2017"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4297/35490469260_a096cce29f_k.jpg" width="2048" height="2033" alt="iPhone Pics from Beartooth Run 2017"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/36417440705/in/album-72157683434776573/" title="iPhone Pics from Beartooth Run 2017"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4342/36417440705_6b4b6b2a76_b.jpg" width="1022" height="1011" alt="iPhone Pics from Beartooth Run 2017"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With that, I'll wrap up today's post. Everyone's feeling pretty excited about the run up to the pass tomorrow morning. Should be a lot of fun! &amp;#x1F6E3;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Beartooth Run, 2017</title><updated>2017-07-06 19:36:59</updated><author><name>oubiwann</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2017-07/06-193659/beartooth-run-2017.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:Beartooth Run, 2017</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We set off bright and early this morning on the first day of a two-day trip to get to &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Red_Lodge,_Montana'&gt;Red Lodge, Montana&lt;/a&gt; in order to participate in the 24th Annual Fargo H.O.G. Beartooth Run. Rory drove the support vehicle which provided two important benefits: she got to come along for the fun and camping, and I didn't have to pack up the bags on the cruiser :-) The only bummer about this was that she wasn't able to ride her Heritage Springer on the trip.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Oddly, at the first stop, I found that I missed having the bags on the bike &amp;ndash; getting cleaning supplies and snacks from the bags, swapping out goggles, etc., was rather cumbersome when doing so when everything was in the support vehicle. Lesson learned for next time!)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class="panel panel-default route-summary"&gt;   &lt;div class="panel-heading"&gt;&lt;h3 class="panel-title"&gt;Day Summary&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/div&gt;   &lt;div class="panel-body"&gt;     &lt;form class="form-horizontal"&gt;       &lt;div class="form-group"&gt;         &lt;label for="summary-start" class="col-sm-3 control-label"&gt;Start:&lt;/label&gt;         &lt;div id="summary-start" class="col-sm-9"&gt; &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sioux_Falls,_South_Dakota'&gt;Sioux Falls, SD&lt;/a&gt;  6:23 am CDT&lt;/div&gt;       &lt;/div&gt;       &lt;div class="form-group"&gt;         &lt;label for="summary-end" class="col-sm-3 control-label"&gt;End:&lt;/label&gt;         &lt;div id="summary-end" class="col-sm-9"&gt; &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Belle_Fourche,_South_Dakota'&gt;Belle Fourche, SD&lt;/a&gt;  4:39 pm CDT&lt;/div&gt;       &lt;/div&gt;       &lt;div class="form-group"&gt;         &lt;label for="summary-miles" class="col-sm-3 control-label"&gt;Distance:&lt;/label&gt;         &lt;div id="summary-miles" class="col-sm-9"&gt;466 mi (750 km)&lt;/div&gt;       &lt;/div&gt;       &lt;div class="form-group"&gt;         &lt;label for="summary-food" class="col-sm-3 control-label"&gt;Food:&lt;/label&gt;         &lt;div id="summary-food" class="col-sm-9"&gt; Lunch @ &lt;a href='http://www.burgershackfaulkton.com/'&gt;The Burger Shack&lt;/a&gt; in Faulkton, SD&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dinner @ Riverside Campground in Belle Fourche, SD         &lt;/div&gt;       &lt;/div&gt;       &lt;div class="form-group"&gt;         &lt;label for="summary-slept" class="col-sm-3 control-label"&gt;Slept:&lt;/label&gt;         &lt;div id="summary-slept" class="col-sm-9"&gt; &lt;a href='http://www.bellefourche.org/index.asp?SEC=793C37DA-55F8-4041-87D2-78A5C98A1F5F&amp;DE=DEF0F545-145E-4899-8A96-A923111669F0&amp;Type=B_BASIC'&gt;Riverside Campground&lt;/a&gt;  (hammocks)&lt;/div&gt;       &lt;/div&gt;       &lt;div class="form-group"&gt;       &lt;label for="summary-photos" class="col-sm-3 control-label"&gt;Photo Album:&lt;/label&gt;         &lt;div id="summary-photos" class="col-sm-9"&gt; &lt;a href='https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/albums/72157683927036270'&gt;Beartooth Run 2017 - Day 1&lt;/a&gt; (Flickr)         &lt;/div&gt;       &lt;/div&gt;     &lt;/form&gt;   &lt;/div&gt;   &lt;div class="panel-heading"&gt;&lt;h3 class="panel-title"&gt;Route Map&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/div&gt;   &lt;div class="panel-body" style="padding:0; margin: 0"&gt;     &lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4416/35585097933_87f753eefd_k_d.jpg"&gt;   &lt;/div&gt;   &lt;div class="panel-heading"&gt;&lt;h3 class="panel-title"&gt;Beartooth Run, 2017 Series Links&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/div&gt;   &lt;div class="panel-body" style="padding:0; margin: 0"&gt;     &lt;ul&gt;       &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/blog/archives/2017-06/29-115623/beartooth-run-fargo-h-o-g-.html"&gt;Prologue&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;       &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/blog/archives/2017-07/06-193659/beartooth-run-2017.html"&gt;Day 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;       &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/blog/archives/2017-07/07-212540/beartooth-run-2017.html"&gt;Day 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;       &lt;li&gt;Day 3&lt;/li&gt;       &lt;li&gt;Day 4&lt;/li&gt;       &lt;li&gt;Day 5&lt;/li&gt;       &lt;li&gt;Day 6&lt;/li&gt;     &lt;/ul&gt;   &lt;/div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href='https://www.facebook.com/fargoharleyownersgroup/'&gt;Fargo H.O.G.&lt;/a&gt; Beartooth Run is a bit of a unique animal for a ride: everyone heads off on their own (or forms rider groups as desired) and then meet in Red Lodge, MT the night before the run up to the pass. Some might find this a bit odd, but it's really great to have that kind of freedom to plan the ride you want.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, I've wanted to ride Beartooth Pass for a while, now &amp;ndash; but I wanted to get there riding &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S._Route_212'&gt;U.S. Route 212&lt;/a&gt; as much of the way as possible. This trip was the perfect excuse :-) So we started day 1 with the goal of getting to US-212 north of Pierre, SD. We ended up taking a little different route due to an unexpected dirt road, some construction, and a detour.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The scenery is pretty typical for eastern South Dakota: flat farmland with small town speckled around. Folks were especially friendly in &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Woonsocket,_South_Dakota'&gt;Woonsocket&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; definitely a great place to stop and get gas or grab a meal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/36225695792/in/album-72157683927036270/" title="Untitled"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4372/36225695792_5772cc0759_c.jpg" width="800" height="600" alt="Untitled"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Next up was &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Faulkton,_South_Dakota'&gt;Faulkton&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/36348772356/in/album-72157683927036270/" title="Untitled"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4342/36348772356_6557a33219_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1536" alt="Untitled"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We got there around lunchtime and had some great burgers (and a strawberry shake!). Big thumbs up on the food, and fun decor to boot:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/35558121434/in/album-72157683927036270/" title="Untitled"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4423/35558121434_794711fee1_c.jpg" width="600" height="800" alt="Untitled"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/36393575835/in/album-72157683927036270/" title="Untitled"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4377/36393575835_f6b27e5c5d_c.jpg" width="600" height="800" alt="Untitled"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/35746908801/in/album-72157683927036270/" title="iPhone Pics from Beartooth Run 2017"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4208/35746908801_6bde22bfe4_c.jpg" width="600" height="800" alt="iPhone Pics from Beartooth Run 2017"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Just after Forest City, we crossed the &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Missouri_River'&gt;Missouri&lt;/a&gt;. As we topped the hill and came around the last curve before the river, an amazing site was waiting for us: the Missouri as I'd never seen it before. It looked nothing like a river in the Midwest or Western states; instead we were looking at an ocean scene in the Caribbean. The blues, azures, greens &amp;ndash; all sparkling in the sun &amp;ndash; it was breath-taking, even more so for the unexpectedness of it. Sadly, we found out later that the GoPro's battery had died during this segment of the ride. At the time a little voice was telling me to pull over and take a picture &amp;ndash; I really should have. I hope I do so the next time I hear such hidden advice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We proceeded to make our way through the &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cheyenne_River_Indian_Reservation'&gt;Cheyenne River Reservation&lt;/a&gt;. As we approached the small town of Faith, the land had started to change a bit, getting a little more interesting (don't get me wrong &amp;ndash; I love the prairie! but in the hot sun, on the bike, when the scenery doesn't change much, you can get the 1000 mile stare, and then comes trouble ...). Things continued to change, keeping the eye and mind engaged, and before we knew it, we were in the town of Newell &amp;ndash; no strangers to bikers, there!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some of the best views all day were to be had as we left the gas station in Newell and headed towards Belle Fourche. Cresting one of the rises, a long, dry vista opened up before us with Sturgis in the distance the the Black Hills on the distant horizon.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By the time late afternoon arrived, we were ready to quit for the day, so we were quite relieved to pull into the Riverside Campground when we did.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/35709087512/in/album-72157683927036270/" title="iPhone Pics from Beartooth Run 2017"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4257/35709087512_d4829cdd94_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1536" alt="iPhone Pics from Beartooth Run 2017"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Still quite hot out, I ran out for ice, a cooler, and some beers and we had a delicious dinner of &lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0002YRNVS/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=B0002YRNVS&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=forgottenroad-20&amp;linkId=ff7211731826a8c75d3a13b5028871ae"&gt;freeze dried lasagna&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src="//ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=forgottenroad-20&amp;l=am2&amp;o=1&amp;a=B0002YRNVS" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" /&gt;. It was too hot for the tent, so we strung up our hammocks and had a late siesta, hung out until dark, and then hauled our tired bones back in the sacks :-)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/35558111694/in/datetaken/" title="Untitled"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4371/35558111694_8327b2ae4f_k.jpg" width="1536" height="2048" alt="Untitled"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;#x1F6E3;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Working with KML and GeoJSON Files</title><updated>2017-07-01 12:38:50</updated><author><name>bobbermac</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2017-07/01-123850/working-with-kml-and-geojson-files.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:Working with KML and GeoJSON Files</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As anyone familiar (not me) with geographic information systems (or "GIS") data can tell you, working with the multitude of data formats, versions of those formats, data entry errors, and inconsistencies, makes GIS data processing a pretty time-consuming task. We've just tried to do very simple things, and it has taken us a few days to get things sorted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Right now at Forgotten Roads, we're evaluating software and data services for use in motorcycle adventure trips. We think we've got a good selection, at least for a first run or two. But before we go into any details on that, we wanted to provide a prelude blog post that can be a head-start for the eager reader and something that we can reference in later posts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Below we'll give a super-quick overview of the main geospatial file formats used by mapping and routes services, and then show you how to work with these files (something that will be very useful when you want to start doing interesting things with your ride routes).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;File Formats&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h4&gt;KML&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Google's ubiquity in so much of the tech world, &lt;code&gt;.kml&lt;/code&gt; files (KML stands for "Keyhole Markup Language") are quite popular. &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keyhole_Markup_Language'&gt;KML&lt;/a&gt; is a type of &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XML'&gt;XML&lt;/a&gt; developed by the company Keyhole, Inc., which specialized in geospatial visualization software. Google bought them in 2004 and turned their product "Earth Viewer" into "Google Earth".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are several versions of this markup language:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Version 2.1 - The last one produced by Google &amp;ndash; this version is still widely used&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Version 2.2 - The first KML version that was submitted to the   &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_Geospatial_Consortium'&gt;Open Geospatial Consortium&lt;/a&gt; (OGC) in 2007&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;2.3 - Published by the OGC in 2015&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most of what we see is still version 2.1.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Really, the thing you need to know about KML is that, among the many, many things that it does, it can specify "traces" or "tracks" (very simple geospatial data, sometimes as little as just latitude and longitude values). The visual routes you see on mapping services like "Google Maps" can be represented in KML files that have this simple data.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;GeoJSON&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the increasing popularity of KML in the mid-2000s, the nearly industry-wide distaste for XML, and rapidly growing adoption of JSON as a preferred human-readable data representation format, a working group for a &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JSON'&gt;JSON&lt;/a&gt;-based geospatial data format was begun in 2007. This gave the world GeoJSON. Then, in 2015, a working group was founded at the &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_Engineering_Task_Force'&gt;IETF&lt;/a&gt; for GeoJSON, which led to an &lt;a href='https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7946'&gt;RFC&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We've been using this format a fair amount, too &amp;ndash; not directly, but because other tools or services we are using work with it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;GPX&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;The last format we'll mention is &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GPS_Exchange_Format'&gt;GPX&lt;/a&gt;. We're not making use of any data in this format, but would remiss if we didn't mention it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Based upon XML, it was created around the same times as KML and stands for "GPS Exchange Format". In continues to enjoy a great deal of popularity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Converting&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Okay, now that we have that boring stuff out of the way, we can talk about MORE BORING STUFF! How do I move from one to the other?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Validating KML&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first thing to keep in mind is that you may download a KML file from a service that has not provided the data fully to spec. Or they may be using an ever older version (and calling it a newer version). This is something that you can check, if you find that services are not letting you upload these KML files.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For instance, if you download a KML file, open it up and check the version number. You should see a line near the top something like the following:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;kml xmlns=&amp;quot;http://earth.google.com/kml/2.1&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;The version number is there at the end. KML is an XML format, and XML file formats are defined with schemas. A quick internet search or two turns up the location for the KML version 2.1 schema here:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://developers.google.com/kml/schema/kml21.xsd'&gt;https://developers.google.com/kml/schema/kml21.xsd&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Here are versions &lt;a href='http://schemas.opengis.net/kml/2.2.0/ogckml22.xsd'&gt;2.2&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href='http://schemas.opengis.net/kml/2.3/ogckml23.xsd'&gt;2.3&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We'll use a command-line tool running in a terminal window for this next bit. The command we'll run is &lt;code&gt;xmllint&lt;/code&gt;. If you have a recent version of Mac OS X with developer tools installed, &lt;code&gt;xmllint&lt;/code&gt; will already be on  your machine. If you are running something like Ubuntu, you may already have &lt;code&gt;libxml2-utils&lt;/code&gt; installed (which includes &lt;code&gt;xmllint&lt;/code&gt;). Here's how you check that the formatting of the KML file is correct:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ xmllint --schema &amp;#126;/Downloads/kml21.xsd &amp;#126;/Downloads/track.kml
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;We downloaded a KML file from &lt;a href='https://spotwalla.com/'&gt;SpotWalla&lt;/a&gt; and found that this command failed on that file. We had to open it up and change a line from this:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;altitudeMode&amp;gt;relative&amp;lt;/altitudeMode&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;to this:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;altitudeMode&amp;gt;relativeToGround&amp;lt;/altitudeMode&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h4&gt;KML -&gt; GeoJSON&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;Probably the easiest way to convert a KML file you have downloaded to GeoJSON is to upload it to the "MyGeodata Converter" service:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://mygeodata.cloud/converter/kml-to-geojson'&gt;https://mygeodata.cloud/converter/kml-to-geojson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Simply browse for your file when you hit the button, then hit "Continue". Once your file uploads, you'll be asked to set any options (the defaults are fine for most cases; we haven't needed to adjust them yet). Then hit the "Convert now!" button, and a &lt;code&gt;.zip&lt;/code&gt; file will download, which you can open up and extract your new &lt;code&gt;.geojson&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The same site offers &lt;a href='https://mygeodata.cloud/converter/geojson-to-gpx'&gt;a GPX converter&lt;/a&gt;, should you need that.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Other Tools&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;We've tried each of the following other tools but they either didn't work for our files or the functionality provided was not quite what we needed. However, they do seem to have a good user following and may be useful for you, so we'll share some links:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://merkaartor.be/'&gt;Merkaartor&lt;/a&gt; - a mapping program that can be used with  &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OpenStreetMap'&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt;; it offers some  import capabilities&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://www.google.com/earth/download/gep/agree.html'&gt;Google Earth Pro&lt;/a&gt; -  Google now provides the "pro" version of their Google Earth software for  free. This is now considered an outdated version; the supported one is the  new Chrome-only Google Earth 9 (released in 2017).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://www.gpsvisualizer.com/map_input?form=googleearth'&gt;GPS Visualizer&lt;/a&gt; -  only used it once, but it seems pretty good.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;KMLCSV - maybe we were doing it wrong, but I wouldn't even bother with this  one ...&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Next Up&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Before too long, you should be seeing another FRMX post about how we use the services that use KML and GeoJSON ... ! &amp;#x1F6E3;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Beartooth Run, Fargo H.O.G.</title><updated>2017-06-29 11:56:23</updated><author><name>oubiwann</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2017-06/29-115623/beartooth-run-fargo-h-o-g-.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:Beartooth Run, Fargo H.O.G.</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well, it's official &amp;ndash; I've just heard that as a new member of the Fargo H.O.G. Chapter, I'm eligible to ride with them on their 24th Annual Beartooth Run! I met a handful of the Fargo member on the &lt;a href='/blog/archives/2017-06/15-223122/dam-ride-2017.html'&gt;Dam Ride&lt;/a&gt;, where two members also from Sioux Falls (Coleen and Mary) told me about &amp;ndash; and encouraged me to go on &amp;ndash; the Fargo H.O.G. &lt;a href='http://www.hdfargo.com/event/beartoothrun/'&gt;Bearthooth Run&lt;/a&gt;. I got the acknowledgment of my registration from their events coordinator, Mallory, today and I'm pretty excited.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's a unique ride with some nice history. We're all going to meet in Red Lodge, arriving on our own (traveling in groups as we see fit), having a pizza dinner sponsored by J &amp; L family of Harley dealerships (&lt;a href='http://www.hdfargo.com/'&gt;Fargo&lt;/a&gt;, in this case) and then setting off the next morning for the annual ride up the pass.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'll be riding without bags, since Rory's going to be driving the Forgotten Roads support vehicle. Here we come, Montana!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class="panel panel-default route-summary"&gt;   &lt;div class="panel-heading"&gt;&lt;h3 class="panel-title"&gt;Planned Route&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/div&gt;   &lt;div class="panel-body" style="padding:0; margin: 0"&gt;     &lt;img src="/blog/img/beartooth-ride-planned.jpg"&gt;   &lt;/div&gt;   &lt;div class="panel-heading"&gt;&lt;h3 class="panel-title"&gt;Beartooth Run, 2017 Series Links&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/div&gt;   &lt;div class="panel-body" style="padding:0; margin: 0"&gt;     &lt;ul&gt;       &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/blog/archives/2017-06/29-115623/beartooth-run-fargo-h-o-g-.html"&gt;Prologue&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;       &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/blog/archives/2017-07/06-193659/beartooth-run-2017.html"&gt;Day 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;       &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/blog/archives/2017-07/07-212540/beartooth-run-2017.html"&gt;Day 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;       &lt;li&gt;Day 3&lt;/li&gt;       &lt;li&gt;Day 4&lt;/li&gt;       &lt;li&gt;Day 5&lt;/li&gt;       &lt;li&gt;Day 6&lt;/li&gt;     &lt;/ul&gt;   &lt;/div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;#x1F6E3;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Themes, Categories, and Tags</title><updated>2017-06-28 00:11:03</updated><author><name>oubiwann</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2017-06/28-001103/themes-categories-and-tags.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:Themes, Categories, and Tags</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of things we want to do very well here at Forgotten Roads:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Get out and have some adventures on &lt;strong&gt;America's byways&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Write stories about the &lt;strong&gt;roads, land, and the people&lt;/strong&gt; that we meet and love&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Share our &lt;strong&gt;learning experiences&lt;/strong&gt; so you can have your own adventures sooner, safer, and happier&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get you excited&lt;/strong&gt; about riding and discovery!&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, we wanted to make sure that the articles stayed true to these basic objectives. Just as importantly, we wanted to make sure you knew up front what a post was focused on. That way, if you don't want to read it, you know that right away, and we're not wasting your time. Conversely, if you're interested in a particular topic, it should be easy keep up.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So here's what we've done:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;THEMES&lt;/strong&gt; - There are two "big" types of articles that will get the most emphasis on FRMX.  More than any others, these are the posts that define us and our purpose:&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;"Forgotten Road" posts - these will be articles that cover one road (or route)     that we found special; perfect for a great ride&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;"Excursionist" posts - these will be about interesting people that inspire and     challenge us&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CATEGORIES&lt;/strong&gt; - After the big-ticket items will be more frequent posts  that cover secondary areas of interest, such as events, long trips,  news items, etc.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TAGS&lt;/strong&gt; - While every post will have only one THEME or CATEGORY, each will likely have  several tags. These are simply meant to provide a pointer to the handful of interesting  topics covered in any given post.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;With that, we hope you enjoy what we write for you, and invite you to &lt;a href='/blog/contact.html'&gt;reach out&lt;/a&gt; if you have any ideas or questions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Happy reading! And remember: adventure is out there! &amp;#x1F6E3;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Update: Lower-48 Challenge</title><updated>2017-06-24 10:55:24</updated><author><name>oubiwann</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2017-06/24-105524/update-lower-48-challenge.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:Update: Lower-48 Challenge</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Wow! &lt;a href='https://www.facebook.com/2ringbike/'&gt;@2ringbike&lt;/a&gt; has made great progress on his &lt;a href='http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog/archives/2017-06/16-170908/the-lower-48-challenge.html'&gt;Lower-48-State Challenge&lt;/a&gt;: last night he was shacked up in Flagstaff, AZ and now he seems to be just minutes from the California border.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He's on day 8 of his 10 day ride &amp;ndash; almost there, 2ringbike! Ride safe!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Update&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;26 June, 2017 0042&lt;/strong&gt;: It looks like, as of about an hour ago, 2ringbike completed his mission! Here's a screenshot of his completed map I just took:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/2ringbike-48-update-2.jpg"&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Congratulations, man!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Get some good sleep and ride home safe :-) &amp;#x1F6E3;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Lessons Learned When Packing a Cruiser for Touring</title><updated>2017-06-18 17:28:28</updated><author><name>oubiwann</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2017-06/18-172828/lessons-learned-when-packing-a-cruiser-for-touring.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:Lessons Learned When Packing a Cruiser for Touring</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last year was my first year of riding, and at the end of the season I took a 3,600 mile trip. Due to a family emergency, I was in a hurry to leave, and as such, barely had time to pack much less figure out how to do this well with a bike set up for cruising and not touring. In the weeks after my return and then over the winter, I spent many an hour looking at bags online, coming up with different arrangements for the bike, packing and re-packing in my mind. This first trip this year gave me a chance to get out of my head and put some of that to the test. Though it was only a 1,000 mile ride, it was still a good test.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;How Not To Do It&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Before the solution, though, let's look at the problem :-)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/35597001871/in/album-72157686061205075/" title="2016-09-11 14.55.19"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4098/35597001871_6bd7e684e6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="2016-09-11 14.55.19"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That's a shot from when I'd made it over the Rockies and was preparing to head down into Durango, CO and on into Arizona and Utah. As you can see, I didn't have much to work with: a backpack strapped illegally across the front headlight, a 5300 cu in mountaineering pack lashed to the rear fender, a large tarp, a tent, rain gear, clothes, etc.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The headlight melted the back of the one pack, but it's still quite usable (except for the hydration pouch in the very back!). For the return trip, I stacked it up on the rear fender with everything else, but then got another smaller bag to put on the front fender for miscellaneous easy-access items:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/34918690363/in/album-72157686061205075/" title="2016-09-17 09.48.25"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4092/34918690363_416587c5af_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="2016-09-17 09.48.25"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It doesn't take too much imagination to put a kitchen sink at the top of that pile ... yet the odd bags weren't the biggest problem: the fact that they were essentially woven to the fenders was. Access to the tent, the air pad, the lined Carhartt pants (I was riding in below-freezing weather in the mountains) required undoing the whole thing. There were times during the trip when I simply slept on the gravel or forest floor with the tarp thrown over me because it was too much trouble to unstrap everything ...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the end of the trip, I did give in at a particularly nice camping spot: I unpacked &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt;. Doing so was such a luxury, it almost felt like I'd gone to a hotel. However, repacking it all in the morning took me about an hour.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/35559295472/in/album-72157686061205075/" title="2016-09-18 19.24.24"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4067/35559295472_8880dd41e5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="2016-09-18 19.24.24"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The parking spot doesn't look like much, but here's a view in the other direction:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/35688496706/in/album-72157686061205075/" title="2016-09-18 19.24.48"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4069/35688496706_9a5578447e.jpg" width="500" height="375" alt="2016-09-18 19.24.48"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Winter Ponderings&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I had an amazing trip. Truly the best 3,600 miles I'd ever traveled using any mode of transport. After resting up for a day at home, I wanted to turn around and do it again. Since this indicated I was completely hooked, my task that winter was one and only one thing: starting from scratch with the whole packing thing, applying everything I'd learned, and coming up with a solution that met a list of requirements I'd been putting together.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A successful bag configuration would allow me to:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Do long distance rides with the cruiser&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Pack and un-pack in mere minutes instead of an hour or more&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Have easy access to all packs, pockets, nooks, and crannies&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Travel for up to two weeks with minimal resupply, and&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Keep everything dry and well-organised&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;I got hung up on saddlebags for a while, and when no solutions presented themselves to my satisfaction, I set that particular part of the problem aside to focus on other, more general bag arrangements. Eventually, I zeroed in on those that could be done on top of one or more of the fenders. After several false starts, I began to seriously explore the &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MOLLE'&gt;MOLLE&lt;/a&gt; route, and with that the solution was near. It turns out MOLLE on the bike works just as well as it does for soldiers in the field (and it's WAAAAAY better than the damn ALICE clips we had to use when I was in the Army). Being able to securely fix multiple bags together in changeable configurations really got me where I needed to be.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;3-to-5 Day Rides&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I quadruple-checked my measurements and began to order bags, one at a time. One reason for this approach was not wanting to go all-in to what could potentially have been a costly mistake. Another reason was also practical, but in a different way: I wanted to make sure each bag could stand on its own and didn't depend upon one or more of the others, just to be useful.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A each bag checked out in flying colors, I made the final purchase and then spent a couple of hours down at the hardware store getting more bolts, nuts, washers (metal and rubber). The end result was ready in time for a 3-day, 2-night test ride through &lt;a href='/blog/archives/2017-06/15-223122/dam-ride-2017.html'&gt;Minnesota, North Dakota, and South Dakota&lt;/a&gt;: the 2017 Dam Ride. The time and thinking paid off:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/34884832524/in/album-72157682878950252/" title="2017-06-15 08.08.30"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4289/34884832524_cbb5ddf526_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="2017-06-15 08.08.30"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That looks a little bit messy only because it's all tied down, cinched-up, and wrapped around itself, ready for the ride. Here's another shot:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/34916598993/in/album-72157682878950252/" title="2017-06-15 08.10.01"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4072/34916598993_f33fa96b78_c.jpg" width="600" height="800" alt="2017-06-15 08.10.01"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even though the bags acting as panniers are different sizes, the one on the left held lighter supplies, so all three bags remained balanced on the fender (which also being strapped down, of course).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This rig consists of the following:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Central bag: &lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0051V2CE0/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=B0051V2CE0&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=forgottenroad-20&amp;linkId=18aff3f2870bd93364bd3db32f64edcb"&gt;Fox Outdoor Products Deluxe Modular Gear Bag, Olive Drab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src="//ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=forgottenroad-20&amp;l=am2&amp;o=1&amp;a=B0051V2CE0" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Right front bag: &lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B003W96GG8/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=B003W96GG8&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=forgottenroad-20&amp;linkId=6101ec290b4e6b0abc2cc62d2cdb8548"&gt;Condor Deployment Bag (Black, 12 x 6 x 5.5-Inch)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src="//ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=forgottenroad-20&amp;l=am2&amp;o=1&amp;a=B003W96GG8" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Left rear bag: &lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00519NR1O/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=B00519NR1O&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=forgottenroad-20&amp;linkId=bbfe7a2b22c2304f13902ac91abf19c2"&gt;Fox Outdoor Products Modular Operator's Bag, Olive Drab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src="//ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=forgottenroad-20&amp;l=am2&amp;o=1&amp;a=B00519NR1O" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Left front bag: &lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B01G07FO8E/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=B01G07FO8E&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=forgottenroad-20&amp;linkId=081f5503c15fb0edb4eca97a232dfb07"&gt;Orca Tactical MOLLE Rip-Away EMT Medical First Aid Pouch (Bag Only) (OD Green)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src="//ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=forgottenroad-20&amp;l=am2&amp;o=1&amp;a=B01G07FO8E" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Tank bag: &lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0051PB40O/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=B0051PB40O&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=forgottenroad-20&amp;linkId=ed87305d4155c96b37405a781d3e424d"&gt;Tactical Map Case Olive Drab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src="//ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=forgottenroad-20&amp;l=am2&amp;o=1&amp;a=B0051PB40O" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not pictured, but also used for 3L of water, some snacks, and additional items:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00AOC1NDC/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=B00AOC1NDC&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=forgottenroad-20&amp;linkId=e3838f6185003f9317ebae955b400587"&gt;Fox Outdoor Products Elite Excursionary Hydration Pack, Olive Drab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src="//ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=forgottenroad-20&amp;l=am2&amp;o=1&amp;a=B00AOC1NDC" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Attaching the Bags&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This bit was a bit tricker. Here's what I did:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Measured where the attachment holes in the rear fender lined up with  the central large gear bag&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Used a leather punch (and a lighter to fix the nylon) and then put brass  grommets around the new holes&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Drilled corresponding holes in the bottom reinforcement that came with  the bag&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Got some new bolts, nuts, and combination of rubber and metal washers  to attach the gear bag to the rear fender&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Made custom straps from 1" nylon webbing and dual-adjust clip buckles&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Fed the straps through the fender supports&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Placed the bag over the straps and bolted it on&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the central bag tightened down, the panniers were ready to be attached using MOLLE straps.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Teardown was easy, but that was also when I discovered that during the 3-day ride, I'd bent the rear bolt and warped the fender a bit at the bolt hole. I've since purchased some steel I'm going to drill some holes in, do some primitive fabrication to curve it in the same way as the fender, and use some different washers for reinforcement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Packing with the Bags&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here's an inside-look at some of the bags (the deployment bag on the other side was full of googles, gloves, bungee cords/nets, etc.):&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/35594814341/in/album-72157682878950252/" title="2017-06-16 05.31.33"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4043/35594814341_eef3dbeff7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="2017-06-16 05.31.33"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The tool wrap is there at the bottom (separate 5-star blog post coming for that guy!), and most of everything else is a collection of weather-proof bags of varying sizes where all the clothes went. You typically see these bags in camping/adventure stores where kayakers and canoers go. I'm glad I ran across them, because they really changed everything for me. (I think the three red small ones I picked up at Walmart where I was getting last-minute supplies.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As great as the Fox tactical bags were for carrying my stuff, these dry bags were the secret sauce for perfect packing. Pros include:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;the obvious, they kept things dry&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;multiple sizes (3 1L bags and 1 3L bag) allowed for easy packing of little  items as well as the bulkier stuff&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;the dry bags fit perfectly in the central "gear" bag and the left pannier&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;they forced me to pack tight and organize according to usage&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;as the trip progressed, their role as dirty laundry bags was just as  important!&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Due to the limitations in volume and number, they really forced me to exercise good packing practices and the results were felt throughout the ride. This is how I want to do it from now on.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, here's a look inside the first-aide kit:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/34916594153/in/album-72157682878950252/" title="2017-06-15 08.06.54"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4010/34916594153_575f0a5cfd_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="2017-06-15 08.06.54"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fortunately nothing there was needed, but the design is so fantastic for quick access to medical supplies that I never unpack it, using it like you see here at home, on hikes, and on rides.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Strapping unneeded clothing and the helmet to the packs was easy and stable, perfect for cruising around the campground. Pulling over into a campsite, setting up the hammock, unpacking for the night, accessing toiletries, etc., with this bag arrangement was a dream:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/forgottenroadsmx/35557196302/in/album-72157682878950252/" title="2017-06-15 17.44.16"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4062/35557196302_675cb91eb1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="2017-06-15 17.44.16"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Such a different experience from last year's big ride!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update&lt;/strong&gt;: Here's another bag I'm looking at, different brand ... and it's REALLY growing on me. Might have to get two of these: &lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00ZWOF7HA/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=B00ZWOF7HA&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=forgottenroad-20&amp;linkId=b5f0cfa708d23e298799e40cd5acadf3"&gt;SHANGRI-LA Tactical Assault Gear Sling Pack Range Bag with Shoulder Strap - Army Green&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src="//ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=forgottenroad-20&amp;l=am2&amp;o=1&amp;a=B00ZWOF7HA" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Epilogue&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Bag Swap&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Resizing: for 2-3 days rides, the left-side operator bag was a bit too large; conversely, the right-side deployment bag was a tiny bit too small. I'd also like them to be the same size, so I'm thinking of going this route next time:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00GKUCZ0W/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=B00GKUCZ0W&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=forgottenroad-20&amp;linkId=1a4fad0c51e8e48e2f20797f029900e1"&gt;Fox Outdoor Products Jumbo Modular Deployment Bag, Digital Woodland&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src="//ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=forgottenroad-20&amp;l=am2&amp;o=1&amp;a=B00GKUCZ0W" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;For 4-7 day rides, I'd swap those out (keeping the large central "gear" bag) for something bigger than the operator's bag with the canyon zipper (nice, but better as a small carry-on when flying):&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00513G5HS/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=B00513G5HS&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=forgottenroad-20&amp;linkId=2f2f75727910f1f2b3e26e4480c84d11"&gt;Fox Outdoor Products Modular Equipment Bag, Olive Drab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src="//ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=forgottenroad-20&amp;l=am2&amp;o=1&amp;a=B00513G5HS" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;With both the jumbo deployment bag as well as the modular equipment bag, you get smaller zippered compartments at both ends. These are my most-used pockets during an actual ride, where I keep things like extra gloves (important when riding in altitude), goggles for day/night, hats for stopping, changes of socks, sunscreen, bug spray, additional snacks, etc.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Front Panniers&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;I haven't come up with a good solution for the front of the bike yet. For last year's trip, a strapped the small deployment bag (the one I used on the right this year) between the forks in the front, but this arrangement was unstable. If I can't find a fender+fork frame for attaching bags, I might just have to fabricate one myself.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the event that this does happen, I'm pretty sure the bags I'll use here will be two of the canyon-mouthed operator bags (used on the left this year). Zippered pockets on the side are a pain when low like the bags would be here, so a single wide top-entry opening would be perfect. I would probably put the tools there, as well as other less-often used and heavy items (road flares, large flashlight, extra batteries, spare cables, extension cords, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;The Return of the Saddlebags&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;I like to do my own leatherwork when I can. The large forkbag where I keep my rain gear was fun; the sheath and strap for the entrenching tool, likewise. I've got a vest and new chaps in the works (both buffalo hide). But the next large project is going to be the saddlebags.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now that I've used the other bags on rides, I know the size and placement of the saddlebags I will design and build &amp;ndash; and I will do so for use in conjunction with the bags mentioned in this post. This will extend my riding capabilities by about 1 to 1.5 weeks. Then add a luggage rack and some fasteners for the sleeping bag, tent, and Therma-Rest ... well, you might not see me for a while ;-) &amp;#x1F6E3;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Bags from this Article&lt;/h2&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Dam Ride 2017</title><updated>2017-06-17 21:27:57</updated><author><name>oubiwann</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2017-06/17-212757/dam-ride-2017.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:Dam Ride 2017</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A review of the third and final day of the South Dakota/North Dakota H.O.G. Chapters' 2017 Dam Ride.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Dam Ride Posts&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='/blog/archives/2017-06/15-223122/dam-ride-2017.html'&gt;Day 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='/blog/archives/2017-06/16-233523/dam-ride-2017.html'&gt;Day 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='/blog/archives/2017-06/17-212757/dam-ride-2017.html'&gt;Day 3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Day 3&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/dam-ride-route-day-3.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This morning we woke to find our bikes had been thoroughly washed by the rain, which was actually quite nice :-) As folks donned their rain gear, there was some discussion about just heading down SD-34 and then straight over to Sioux Falls to avoid the weather. Fortunately, the consensus evolved towards finishing the full ride, and we soon headed out into the cloudy morning, our tanks brimming with petrol.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pierre is a small city, and within moments we were in open land. SD-34 is a nice road, and since it follows the Missouri River for a while, it's got a stretch of great scenery. After it pulls away from the river, it passes through the &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crow_Creek_Indian_Reservation'&gt;Crow Creek Reservation&lt;/a&gt; which offers a beauty of its own:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/dam-ride-crow-creek-reservation.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After hanging a right in Fort Thompson towards the Missouri, we stopped at the &lt;a href='http://www.crowcreekconnections.org/photos.html'&gt;Spirit of the Circle Monument&lt;/a&gt; (dedicated to the loss of Santee Lakota lives in the aftermath of the Dakota War of 1862). This was my second visit to the site; it is a rightfully somber but peaceful place. Then we headed across the river and stopped at the bottom of &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Bend_Dam'&gt;Big Bend Dam&lt;/a&gt;, continuing westward after snapping a picture of the group.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So far, the stretch of road we'd done that morning had been some of the best riding of the whole event: the temperature had dropped quite a bit, making the quite comfortable (I prefer cool rides); no rain yet, even though everyone in the group but me was in rain gear (I was in my leathers; I often don't care if I get wet while riding ... unless I'm camping for the night!). The roads were smooth, there was no traffic, the group seemed in good spirits, and the land engulfing us was beautiful and peaceful.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As nice as that was, it was about to get better :-) On SD-47, especially once we passed under and were south of Interstate 90, and as we got up into the hills in that area. Google Street View can't really capture it, but this &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; give you a sense of it:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/dam-ride-hwy-47-sd.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mark and I had swapped out the sweep position, so I'd been in the back, but as we moved down 47, I kept loosing track of place and time and would often find that I'd eased off the throttle so much that the group was way ahead. It brought a smile to my face a few times when I'd caught up and saw that the &lt;em&gt;whole group&lt;/em&gt; was spread out like that ... as if we were expanding to drink it all in, each person riding in their own private vastness :-)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After that section of the road when we filled up in Gregory, SD several of us expressed the same sentiment: let's go back and ride that again!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You will definitely be seeing a dedicated "Forgotten Road" post from me on SD-47 ... with tons of pictures and notes on things to look for when you are riding through that beautiful, open country.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While we were filling up at the station, we had a nice conversation with a local farmer; we'd told him how amazed we were with the ride, what special country it was, and he beamed with a soft pride. There was a nice bond we formed in loving that land, land that he quite obviously took a special pride and honor in.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a bonus, he shared with us his favourite place to eat down the road in Pickstown. None of us willing to skip lunch like we'd done the day before, we eagerly hopped on our bikes in search Abby's.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/dam-ride-abbys.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yup, that's Abby's. I gotta say, when we passed the steakhouse/burger place with the "Biker's Welcome" sign and instead pulled into a gas station for eats, I had some serious doubts. However, there are a bunch of tables inside and a couple short-order cooks in an ample kitchen. The service was prompt and very friendly. As we waited for our food the place &lt;strong&gt;really&lt;/strong&gt; filled up; by the time we were stuffing our faces with the best lunch of the ride, the joint was packed. We thanked that farmer for the tip, wherever he was then :-)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While in Abby's, the rain had finally caught up to us with some gentle sprinkles sending us off to see the last dam of our ride: &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gavins_Point_Dam'&gt;Gavins Point Dam&lt;/a&gt;. The area around this dam was quite nice &amp;ndash; very family oriented; lots of folks obviously having a wonderful time. The surrounding parkland was open, spacious, inviting, and with lots of it. Seemed like a great place to spend a Sunday afternoon, just hangin' out :-)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With our mission accomplished (visiting all four of the dams on the main route), feeling more rain coming, and ready to be home, we set off. The rain really started coming down as we headed up US-81 &amp;ndash; I was feeling it pretty good, since I'd forgotten to put my keffiyeh back over my lower face after stopping at the dam.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the sky darkened further, and the sky set in for a good pour, we ran into impassable construction and were directed to turn around. This was actually a bonus for me, since I love riding through Viborg and taking smaller country roads home (81's too fast with too much traffic for my taste!)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The rain kept coming down harder and harder, until one point where, just as we came into Sioux Falls, it became a sheer wall of water we were riding through. Seemed like a great way to end a good ride on a hot summer's evening :-) (though I may stand alone with that opinion ... !)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We went our separate ways, changed up, dried off, and then headed over to Lonnie Entenman's (the "L" of "J&amp;L Harley Davidson") secret HD-Cave, chock full of Harley-Davidson memorabilia. I've never seen anything like it ... maybe I can talk him into an interview and a tour with pictures, so I can share it here; it's really something to see.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here's my favourite piece in the place:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/dam-ride-collection.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We all shared our last meal of the event together, told stories, laughed at jokes, and had a really wonderful time together. This was a great event with just the best folks you could want to hang out with, and I'm already looking forward to next year's ride (which may be a trip out to the Black Hills! Hellllo, CAMPING!) &amp;#x1F6E3;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Dam Ride 2017</title><updated>2017-06-16 23:35:23</updated><author><name>oubiwann</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2017-06/16-233523/dam-ride-2017.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:Dam Ride 2017</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A review of the second day of the South Dakota/North Dakota H.O.G. Chapters' 2017 Dam Ride.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Dam Ride Posts&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='/blog/archives/2017-06/15-223122/dam-ride-2017.html'&gt;Day 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='/blog/archives/2017-06/16-233523/dam-ride-2017.html'&gt;Day 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='/blog/archives/2017-06/17-212757/dam-ride-2017.html'&gt;Day 3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Lindenwood Campground&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sleep was a bit fitful last night for me, as it always is when camping in the open without a tent, especially when it's been a while. The noises of nearby Interstate 94 didn't actually bother me, since I had earplugs with me. At 5am I decided I wasn't going to get back to sleep, so I hopped out of the hammock and did my morning routine &amp;ndash; and boy was I glad I did! This is the sunrise that greeted me when I'd finished up:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/dam-ride-sunrise.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My camping neighbor/fellow rider and I packed up and set off about the same time, but we parted ways on the road as he headed off to begin his Lower 48 States challenge and I rode down to the local Harley-Davidson store to meet up with the others joining the Dam Ride.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Day 2&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/dam-ride-route-day-2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the troops slowly made their way in, coffee and donuts helped wake folks up and riding groups started to take shape. It was a slow, casual start and our group was ready to head out around 930am. Sadly, we had decided to take Interstate 94 west (I'm a byways person myself), but fortunately it was just for a few miles.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Shortly after that, we were heading south on country roads like this:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/dam-ride-hwy-1-nd.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(The pics I'd taken at the campground were the only ones for the rest of the trip, so all the rest will be from Google Street View ...)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We made several quick stops for gas, refreshments, visits to the loo, map checks, etc.  Sadly we never stopped for lunch. We did hit some rain, but it was light an we didn't gear up. It felt really nice :-)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At one point, the guy riding sweep (Mark &amp;ndash; we rode together on Day 1 to Fargo) fell back to the point where I lost sight of him. I stopped and pulled a U-ey on the highway and headed back. Almost immediately I caught sight of him, so turned around again. Pretty far behind now, he and I stopped shortly after that when he pulled up next to me and let me know my hydration pack was open at the top and stuff was peeking out.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Well, it turns out that the reason he had stopped the &lt;em&gt;first&lt;/em&gt; time was because he'd seen something fly out and land on the side of the road &amp;mdash; and, of course, it turned out to  be mine! I still owe him a drink for that ...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The roughest part of the ride for everyone (many jokes were made about it at the tailgate party tonight) was the stretch of road along the Missouri river between the area around Forest City, SD and our first dam &amp;ndash; primarily South Dakota Highway 1804:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/dam-ride-sd-1804.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was warm, the scenery didn't seem to change at all, and everyone's energy felt low.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We were all pretty wiped by the time we got to &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oahe_Dam'&gt;Oahe Dam&lt;/a&gt;, so it was nice to stretch and hang out at the visitor's center for a while. We got a nice impromptu tutorial of some high-water events from one of the women who worked there, and that was pretty interesting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As we were gearing up for the final stretch into Pierre, a woman on a Harley trike and her grandson were pulling into the parking lot, the little boy staring wide-eyed at us. We chatted with her a bit, and then asked her shy rider "Hey buddy, how you likin' the ride?" He threw both arms up into the air and yelled out with glee "Weeee-heee!" This cracked all of us up and we gave him cheers of encouragement :-)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After bidding our new friends a safe ride, we were on our way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ride into Pierre was quick, and we were soon at the &lt;a href='https://goo.gl/ndtQ5D'&gt;Ramkota Hotel&lt;/a&gt;, checked in, bikes parked, some of us in shorts, but all of us hanging out in the parking lot with the Fargo HD truck and trailer enjoying free beers, hard ciders, and pop.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Next, we headed over to &lt;a href='https://goo.gl/3JhXbT'&gt;Guadalajara Mexican Restaurant&lt;/a&gt;. It was pretty good (I have to make allowances at Mexican food joints, since I spent the first eight years of my life eating enchiladas in San Diego county), but since we'd missed lunch, I ate waaay more than I should have. They served Modelo Negra, which was a great and unexpected treat &amp;ndash; it's one of my faviourite Mexican beers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One sad thing that happened as we were coming into Pierre was that a young man had gotten into an accident on a motorcycle. A couple in our group from Parker, SD were with us at this point, one of whom had been an EMT for years (now retired; their bike is decked out in a pretty cool EMT-themed paint job). They quickly ran over to assist and were there before the first responders. Fortunately the young man wasn't seriously injured, though he did seem to have a fractured pelvis. Our EMT buddy latter told us that the accident had occurred when a driver ran a red light and clipped the rider (who was a car salesman; he was only out on the road to evaluate the motorcycle which was being used as a trade-in for a car).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was really fantastic to see members of our group leap into action to help those in need. It's also nice to know you're riding with such good people :-) &amp;#x1F6E3;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>The Lower-48 Challenge</title><updated>2017-06-16 17:09:08</updated><author><name>oubiwann</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2017-06/16-170908/the-lower-48-challenge.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:The Lower-48 Challenge</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Shortly after I started riding a motorcycle, I heard about the &lt;a href='http://www.hokaheychallenge.com/index.html'&gt;Hoka Hey Challenge&lt;/a&gt; (more on this later!). Researching that &amp;ndash; and endurance riding in general &amp;ndash; led me to the &lt;a href='http://www.ironbutt.com/'&gt;Iron Butt Association&lt;/a&gt; web site and their rides/certifications. So, when I pulled into my campsite last night and found that I was bivouacked next to someone doing the IBA's &lt;a href='http://www.ironbutt.com/themerides/48n10/'&gt;48 States Series&lt;/a&gt;, I was quite chuffed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='https://www.facebook.com/2ringbike/'&gt;@2ringbike&lt;/a&gt; seems a private man (he didn't give his name, and I didn't ask), but he was eager to have a quiet chat with another rider.  He'd just left home in Saskatchewan, Canada yesterday ... and was already sharing his ride status with his kids and wife (via &lt;a href='https://spotwalla.com/index.php'&gt;SpotWalla&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href='http://bubblergps.com/'&gt;Bubbler GPS&lt;/a&gt;).  He's also riding with a GoPro which is configured to take a still shot every few seconds; he plans on compiling these into a video time-lapse of his trip and putting it on YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This morning he starts on his journey of the lower 48 states. He's going to hop across the state border to Minnesota, then come back to North Dakota and head down to South Dakota, then on to Nebraska and points East after that.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was delighted to be there at the start of his journey, and play some small role in his story &amp;ndash; last night we used my phone's Yelp app (so that he didn't have to pay exorbitant international data fees) to find a coffeeshop where he can get his first certification today.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I can't think of a more excellent way to begin a morning ride than with a cappuccino :-) &amp;#x1F6E3;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Dam Ride 2017</title><updated>2017-06-15 22:31:22</updated><author><name>oubiwann</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2017-06/15-223122/dam-ride-2017.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:Dam Ride 2017</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A review of the first day of the South Dakota/North Dakota H.O.G. Chapters' 2017 Dam Ride.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Dam Ride Posts&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='/blog/archives/2017-06/15-223122/dam-ride-2017.html'&gt;Day 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='/blog/archives/2017-06/16-233523/dam-ride-2017.html'&gt;Day 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='/blog/archives/2017-06/17-212757/dam-ride-2017.html'&gt;Day 3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Three-day HOG-sponsored Ride&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last year the local HOG sponsored a group ride that visited some of the hydro-electric dams in South Dakota, but I wasn't able to go. This year, I took time off from work to make sure I could participate in the three-day ride with three sister HOG chapters. I lucked out, because this year was a full-on event, complete with pin set, tail-gate party, sponsored meals, and support vehicles (which fortunately weren't needed).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;The Route&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since the starting point is in Fargo, ND this year, those of us riding up from Sioux Falls and Glacier Lakes got an early start on our ride. More on that below. The &lt;em&gt;official&lt;/em&gt; ride starts from Fargo, ND with open ended routes across the state to the Missouri and down into South Dakota for a night in Pierre.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The next day is a ride across Native reservations, ranch land, and country roads, the James River valley, Yankton, and up to Sioux Falls.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Preparation&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;On my last multi-day ride (3500+ miles), I was brand-new to distance riding and had quite the adventure with bags and packing &amp;ndash; not only was the trip on short notice, I didn't have any proper bags. All winter I'd been musing about bag arrangement and packing for my cruiser (Softail Slim S). That's a saga that will get a post of its own, but for now I will say that I put a LOT of thinking into the packing and preparation for this smaller ride ... it's going to be the first test of the next iteration of my packing system.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In my eagerness to see if everything fit (it did!), I got it all packed before taking any photos, but at the last minute my wife did remind me to get a shot of the gear that I will be wearing:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/dam-ride-gear-layout.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bright and early, a buddy from the local HOG group and I headed out, everything fully secure and packed tight:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/dam-ride-pre.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Day 1&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/dam-ride-route-day-1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We decided to take a scenic route just across the Minnesota border that would put us into Ortonville in time for lunch. This was my second trip up through this area (the first time was to visit the grave of Medal of Honor war hero &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Woodrow_W._Keeble'&gt;Woodrow Keeble&lt;/a&gt;). Last fall when I stopped in Ortonville they were having their annual corn harvest festival. This time was comparatively sedate, but even more delicious: we had burgers at the excellent &lt;a href='https://goo.gl/pZECGS'&gt;Headwaters Grill &amp; Bar&lt;/a&gt;. Yet another good reason to stop in Ortonville!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The post-lunch ride was really fantastic &amp;ndash; nothing earth-shattering like riding the Rockies or Highway 1 to Big Sur, but just plain fun with beautiful scenery along &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Stone_Lake'&gt;Big Stone Lake&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lake_Traverse'&gt;Lake Traverse&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This last leg of the journey was a bit windy and we sometimes got smacked pretty hard, but the views were so great that the time passed without even feeling it; before we knew it, we were in Fargo. We may actually have been the first riders to arrive:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/dam-ride-fargo.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This gave me enough time to head over to &lt;a href='http://www.fargoparks.com/facilities-recreation/lindenwood-campground.html'&gt;Lindenwood Campground&lt;/a&gt; where they gave me a great site right on the &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Red_River_of_the_North'&gt;Red River&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/dam-ride-red-river.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/dam-ride-camp-site.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Next up was a return to Harley-Davidson of Fargo for the kick-off party+BBQ,  then back to the campsite to set up the hammock, meet &lt;a href='/blog/archives/2017-06/16-170908/the-lower-48-challenge.html'&gt;2ringbike&lt;/a&gt;, and get some shut-eye:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/dam-ride-hammock.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;#x1F6E3;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Nation of Patriots 2017</title><updated>2017-06-07 16:59:57</updated><author><name>oubiwann</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2017-06/07-165957/nation-of-patriots-2017.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:Nation of Patriots 2017</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='/blog/archives/2016-08/25-174345/nation-of-patriots-2016.html'&gt;Last year&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href='http://www.nationofpatriots.com/'&gt;Nation of Patriots&lt;/a&gt; tour came through Sioux Falls, I participated in the mini-parade we took down to the &lt;a href='http://www.siouxfalls.org/veterans-memorial.aspx'&gt;Sioux Falls Veterans' Memorial Park&lt;/a&gt;. We did the same thing this year, but then several of us also rode down to Nebraska for the next passing of the flag ceremony, too.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This year was a bit different &amp;ndash; we were the sixth stop from the start, as opposed to last year where we were the sixth from the last :-) Here's this year's tour path:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/nat-of-pats-2017-path.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As such, the riders came in from Watertown, SD this year instead of Nebraska, to meet us at &lt;a href='http://www.jl-harley.com/'&gt;J&amp;L Harley-Davidson&lt;/a&gt; (not unlike the path taken by &lt;a href='/blog/archives/2017-06/24-105524/update-lower-48-challenge.html'&gt;2ringbike&lt;/a&gt; for his lower-48 IBA challenge ...):&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/nat-of-pats-2017-jlharley.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(photo from the Nation of Patriots Flickr &lt;a href='https://www.flickr.com/photos/149200032@N04/34598215283/in/album-72157682281779824/'&gt;photo stream&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Passing of the Flag in Sioux Falls&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://media.graytvinc.com/images/690*388/patriot+ride.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Photo credit: &lt;a href='http://www.ksfy.com/content/news/Patriot-Ride-stops-in-Sioux-Falls-Tuesday&amp;ndash;426893231.html'&gt;KSFY/ABC Sioux Falls&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I arrived at J &amp; L, I was stunned by how many folks were there, ready to make a parade down to the Veterans' Park! We even had a police escort &amp;ndash; this was a much bigger deal than last year, and it was really nice to see. I think there might have been 20-30 bikes this time (as opposed to the small handful in 2016).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The flag-passing ceremony was nice, recognizing our veterans and give some history/context of the mission of Nation of Patriots. Afterwards,  just like last time, we all signed the book at the park (but no banner was traveling with the flag this year).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;J&amp;L sponsored burgers and dogs for vets up at the "Harley Fort" on 60th, so a bunch of us headed back up after the ceremony. I got to chat with a couple of vets that hadn't been here last year, but had heard of the event this time due to the efforts of the Vietnam/Legacy Vets MC and J &amp; L Harley-Davidson.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;The Ride Down to Norfolk, NE&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The next day I took a day off from work so I could ride with the group down to Norfolk for the next passing of the flag ceremony. This was a great ride, since we didn't take the highway. Lots of great country to ride through, between here and there. Even better, we stopped in Yankton, SD for lunch where &lt;a href='http://jodeans.com/'&gt;JoDean's Steakhouse &amp; Buffet&lt;/a&gt; sponsored lunch for the whole crew! Thanks, JoDean's :-)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I sat with the American Legion commander for Norfolk, NE and he was just the nicest guy I'd hung out with in ages &amp;ndash; if the Norfolk crew is anything like him, they must be a wonderful bunch to work and ride with!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From Yankton we headed down 81 into Nebraska, eventually making our way to the &lt;a href='https://veterans.nebraska.gov/norfolk-veterans-home'&gt;Norfolk Veterans' Home&lt;/a&gt; where they were having a whole-day mini-fair: goats and calves for the kids to pet, balloon sculpture, free lemonade, gunny sack races, big band music, and even a little dancing! There were at least 4 generations represented there; what a wonderful gift to the veterans staying in that home (and it really felt like a &lt;i&gt;home&lt;/i&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After we had a chance to chat, meet some folks, and have some lemonade, we held the ceremony:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/nat-of-pats-2017-1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/nat-of-pats-2017-2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;The Sioux Falls Return Trip&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;After some more mingling and saying goodbye to our new Norfolk friends, we plotted courses back to Sioux Falls. The guys from the MC wanted to zip back up via I-29 (not a fan), so three others of us looked for a scenic route &amp;ndash; which we found!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This was the best riding of the whole two days: all backroads, some time on the &lt;a href='http://nebraskaoutlawtrail.org/'&gt;Outlaw Trail&lt;/a&gt; (a Nebraska Scenic Byway), beautiful hills, some nice curving roads, cute little towns &amp;ndash; in other words, everything you'd want in a ride :-)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Funnily enough, even though we took our sweet time, when we were gassing up in Vermilion, SD we saw the guys from the MC pass by on their way to I-29. We waved, but then continued our ride directly north, taking in the sights and smells, ending our participation this year in the best way: remembering our fellow veterans, freedom of the road, and riding with friends :-) &amp;#x1F6E3;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can find the Nation of Patriots on social media at the following locations:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://twitter.com/NationoPatriots'&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://www.facebook.com/Nation-of-Patriots-193006514043230/'&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://www.flickr.com/photos/149200032@N04/albums'&gt;Flickr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>The Beginning of a New Project</title><updated>2016-09-19 22:13:43</updated><author><name>bobbermac</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2016-09/19-221343/the-beginning-of-a-new-project.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:The Beginning of a New Project</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the things that I enjoy most about riding a motorcycle is the adventure; however, I don't ride a dual-sport bike; I ride a cruiser. I love the old look of the bobber motorcycles, but I like heading off into the unknown on forgotten byways and country roads &amp;ndash; tying a tarp to the bike as lean-to when it's time to rest, and then packing up in the dawn light for another day of sights and smells of the less-traveled lands.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It seems that I'm not alone in this, yet there aren't many places online where one can read stories, take inspiration, or plan for the next such adventure. So, some friends and I thought it might be nice to provide one.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Forgotten Roads is for &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; type of rider who's looking for kindred spirits of the tarmac, gravel, and dirt. We're not an MC, but rather an &lt;em&gt;MX&lt;/em&gt;; not a club, but a resource for the &lt;em&gt;motorcycle excursionist&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the coming months (and years!) you can expect posts on this blog that cover everything from personal adventures and stories to group events and rides; from lessons learned and hard-one personal experience to produce reviews. Of particular interest, we will be sharing excellent roads for riding, and how to get to them, as well as friendships and acquaintances we form with random fellow excursionists we meet on these forgotten roads. &amp;#x1F6E3;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Nation of Patriots 2016</title><updated>2016-08-25 17:43:45</updated><author><name>oubiwann</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2016-08/25-174345/nation-of-patriots-2016.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:Nation of Patriots 2016</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Every year in Sioux Falls, &lt;a href='http://www.jl-harley.com/'&gt;J&amp;L Harley-Davidson&lt;/a&gt; takes part in the &lt;a href='http://www.nationofpatriots.com/'&gt;Nation of Patriots&lt;/a&gt; tour through the lower 48 contiguous states of the US. It starts on &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Memorial_Day'&gt;Memorial Day&lt;/a&gt; and takes about 100 days to complete, covering nearly 15,000 miles in the process.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href='http://www.nationofpatriots.com/tour'&gt;their site&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt; Every year Nation of Patriots&amp;trade; organizes a national effort that pays tribute to, and honors, all of America's Armed Forces - Past, Present, and Fallen. This united effort is known as the Patriot Tour&amp;trade;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Patriot Tour&amp;trade; traditionally begins during Memorial Day weekend. A massive group of riders escorts one American Flag on the back of a motorcycle to the first of many destinations. Upon arrival, the flag is transferred to the new escort. The next day the Flag is escorted to another designated location...and on and on for over 100 days, through all 48 continental states. The Flag finally makes it full circle and lands right back in WI where several thousand Americans gather to honor America's Military members and raise support for those wounded in their service. This is the Patriot Tour&amp;trade;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's the very foundation of the American Flag and all it represents that our brave men and women in the military have stood and died defending, continue to stand and protect, and will forever fight for. &lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The flag arrived today from Nebraska and we had a small group gathered at the &lt;a href='http://www.siouxfalls.org/veterans-memorial.aspx'&gt;Sioux Falls Veterans' Memorial Park&lt;/a&gt;. The group consisted of members from the Vietnam/Legacy Vets MC, H.O.G. Chapter members, employees from J&amp;L, and local veterans. The crew from the MC lead the ride from J&amp;L to the memorial park where we held the passing of the flag ceremony:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/nat-of-pats-2016-1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/nat-of-pats-2016-2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/nat-of-pats-2016-3.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Afterwards, we rode back up to J&amp;L where we signed the banner that was getting passed this year with the flag, talked about the ride up to Watertown tomorrow (where the next flag-passing will occur), and hung out.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The guys from the MC were great, and I got a bunch of their cards. I hope to ride with them again sometime.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Looking forward to participating in the Nation of Patriots next year, too! &amp;#x1F6E3;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can find the Nation of Patriots on social media at the following locations:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://twitter.com/NationoPatriots'&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://www.facebook.com/Nation-of-Patriots-193006514043230/'&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Knucklehead at Sturgis</title><updated>2016-07-31 11:49:41</updated><author><name>oubiwann</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2016-07/31-114941/knucklehead-at-sturgis.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:Knucklehead at Sturgis</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My wife and I were camping in the Black Hills this weekend, just as Sturgis is kicking into gear, and there are some amazing bikes on the road &amp;ndash; tons of group rides going on. The best sight of the day, though, has been the group of vintage Harleys and Indians we saw stopped at a burger joint on the side of the road. I pulled over real quick to snap some photos ...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/arctic-knucklehead-front.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The owner was chatting with another fellow, so I didn't get a chance to say much more than how much I liked is ride, but I did overhear that he had taken two trips to the Arctic Circle with his Knucklehead, and had put something far over 100,000 miles on it, with 2,600 miles of that being gravel roads. The second trip to the Arctic he had done for a buddy who wanted to make the trip with him.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/arctic-knucklehead-side.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He loves adventure riding with the Knucklehead because it's so easy to fix: every time he's had a breakdown, he's been able to get it up and running with the tools he carried on him, even if just to limp along to the nearest garage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm kind of bummed that I only got the boots of the one guy - he was riding an Indian with a group of others, all of them dressed up in period racing gear. What a site! I guess I'll have to go back next year and get more photos :-) &amp;#x1F6E3;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>