<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed</id><updated>2016-09-19 22:13:43</updated><title type="text">Blog for Forgotten Roads MX</title><link rel="self" href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog/blog/atom.xml"></link><entry><title>The Beginning of a New Project</title><updated>2016-09-19 22:13:43</updated><author><name>Duncan</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2016-09/19-221343/the-beginning-of-a-new-project.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:The Beginning of a New Project</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the things that I enjoy most about riding a motorcyle is the adventure; however, I don't ride a dual-sport bike; I ride a cruiser. I love the old look of the bobber motorcyles, but I like heading off into the unknown on forgotten byways and country roads &amp;ndash; tying a tarp to the bike as lean-to when it's time to rest, and then packing up in the dawn light for another day of sights and smells of the less-traveled lands.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It seems that I'm not alone in this, yet there aren't many places online where one can read stories, take inspriation, or plan for the next such adventure. So, I thought it might be nice to provide one.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Forgotten Roads is for &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; type of rider who's looking for kindred spirits of the tarmac, gravel, and dirt. We're not an MC, but rather an &lt;em&gt;MX&lt;/em&gt;; not a club, but a resource for the &lt;em&gt;motorcycle excursionist&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the coming months (and years!) you can expect posts on this blog that cover everything from personal adventures and stories to group events and rides; from lessons learned and hard-one personal experience to produce reviews. Of particular interest will be sharing excellent roads for riding, and how to get to them as well as friendships and aquantainces we form with random fellow excursionists we meet on these forgotten roads.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>