<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed</id><updated>2017-06-24 10:55:24</updated><title type="text">Forgotten Roads MX</title><link rel="self" href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog/blog/atom.xml"></link><entry><title>Update: Lower-48 Challenge</title><updated>2017-06-24 10:55:24</updated><author><name>oubiwann</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2017-06/24-105524/update-lower-48-challenge.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:Update: Lower-48 Challenge</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Wow! &lt;a href='https://www.facebook.com/2ringbike/'&gt;@2ringbike&lt;/a&gt; has made great progress: last night he was shacked up in Flagstaff, AZ and now he seems to be just minutes from the California border.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He's on day 8 of his 10 day ride &amp;ndash; almost there, 2ringbike! Ride safe!&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>The Lower-48 Challenge</title><updated>2017-06-16 17:09:08</updated><author><name>oubiwann</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2017-06/16-170908/the-lower-48-challenge.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:The Lower-48 Challenge</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Shortly after I started riding, I heard about the &lt;a href='http://www.hokaheychallenge.com/index.html'&gt;Hoka Hey Challenge&lt;/a&gt; (more on this later!). Researching that &amp;ndash; and endurance riding in general &amp;ndash; led me to the &lt;a href='http://www.ironbutt.com/'&gt;Iron Butt Association&lt;/a&gt; web site and their rides/certifications. So, when I pulled into my campsite tonight and found that I was bivouacked next to someone doing the IBA's &lt;a href='http://www.ironbutt.com/themerides/48n10/'&gt;48 States Series&lt;/a&gt;, I was quite chuffed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='https://www.facebook.com/2ringbike/'&gt;@2ringbike&lt;/a&gt; seems a private man (he didn't give his name, and I didn't ask), but he was eager to have a quiet chat with another rider.  He just left home in Saskatchewan, Canada today, already sharing his ride status with his kids and wife (via &lt;a href='https://spotwalla.com/index.php'&gt;SpotWalla&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href='http://bubblergps.com/'&gt;Bubbler GPS&lt;/a&gt;).  He's also riding with a GoPro which is configured to take a still shot every few seconds; he plans on compiling these into a video time-lapse of his trip and putting it on YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow morning he starts on his journey of the lower 48 states. He's going to hop across the state border to Minnesota, then come back to North Dakota and head down to South Dakota, then on to Nebraska and points East after that.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was delighted to be there at the start of his journey, and play some small role in his story &amp;ndash; we used my phone's Yelp app (so that he didn't have to pay exorbitant international data fees) to find a coffeeshop where he can get his first certification in the morning. I couldn't think of a more excellent way to begin a morning ride that with a cappuccino :-)&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>The Beginning of a New Project</title><updated>2016-09-19 22:13:43</updated><author><name>bobbermac</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2016-09/19-221343/the-beginning-of-a-new-project.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:The Beginning of a New Project</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the things that I enjoy most about riding a motorcycle is the adventure; however, I don't ride a dual-sport bike; I ride a cruiser. I love the old look of the bobber motorcycles, but I like heading off into the unknown on forgotten byways and country roads &amp;ndash; tying a tarp to the bike as lean-to when it's time to rest, and then packing up in the dawn light for another day of sights and smells of the less-traveled lands.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It seems that I'm not alone in this, yet there aren't many places online where one can read stories, take inspiration, or plan for the next such adventure. So, I thought it might be nice to provide one.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Forgotten Roads is for &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; type of rider who's looking for kindred spirits of the tarmac, gravel, and dirt. We're not an MC, but rather an &lt;em&gt;MX&lt;/em&gt;; not a club, but a resource for the &lt;em&gt;motorcycle excursionist&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the coming months (and years!) you can expect posts on this blog that cover everything from personal adventures and stories to group events and rides; from lessons learned and hard-one personal experience to produce reviews. Of particular interest will be sharing excellent roads for riding, and how to get to them as well as friendships and acquaintances we form with random fellow excursionists we meet on these forgotten roads.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Knucklehead at Sturgis</title><updated>2016-07-31 11:49:41</updated><author><name>oubiwann</name></author><link href="http://forgotten.roads.mx/blog//blog/archives2016-07/31-114941/knucklehead-at-sturgis.html"></link><id>urn:forgotten-roads-mx/blog:feed:post:Knucklehead at Sturgis</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My wife and I were camping in the Black Hills this weekend, just as Sturgis is kicking into gear, and there are some amazing bikes on the road &amp;ndash; tons of group rides going on. The best sight of the day, though, has been the group of vintage Harleys and Indians we saw stopped at a burger joint on the side of the road. I pulled over real quick to snap some photos ...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/arctic-knucklehead-front.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The owner was chatting with another fellow, so I didn't get a chance to say much more than how much I liked is ride, but I did overhear that he had taken two trips to the Arctic Cicle with his Knucklehead, had put something far over 100,000 miles on it, with 2,600 miles of that being gravel roads.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/img/arctic-knucklehead-side.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He loves adventure riding with the Knucklehead because it's so easy to fix: every time he's had a breakdown, he's been able to get it up and running with the tools he carried on him, even if just to limp along to the nearest garage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm kind of bummed that I only got the boots of the one guy - he was riding an Indian with a group of others, all of them dressed up in period racing gear. What a site! I guess I'll have to go back next year and get more photos :-)&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>